<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
	<channel>
		<title>Amelia McNamara</title>
		<description>Amelia McNamara, assistant professor of statistics in the Department of Computer &amp; Information Sciences at the University of St Thomas</description>		
		<link>https://www.amelia.mn</link>
		<atom:link href="https://www.amelia.mn/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Wikipedia in the classroom: Gender, argh</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/sds236/&quot;&gt;data journalism course&lt;/a&gt; I’m teaching this semester is a new offering for me. I may write up more of my reflections later, but for now I wanted to get some thoughts down about the experience of using Wikipedia as a pedagogical tool. At this point, I feel like it was too real-world of an experience for the class, and I inadvertently exposed my students to some gendered bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For their first writing assignment in the class (I am nothing if not ambitious!) I had the students author Wikipedia articles for people who did not have them. You can look at my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/sds236/Wikipedia.html&quot;&gt;assignment guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, but essentially I wanted them to research and write an article, but I gave credit for completion, rather than quality (particularly by Wikipedia’s metric). I generated a list of folks I thought were notable enough for articles, but told students they could choose someone else if they had an idea they wanted to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that not everyone I thought was notable actually had enough material on the web to meet the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Notability&quot;&gt;Wikipedia notability standards&lt;/a&gt;. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Charlotte_Wickham&quot;&gt;Charlotte Wickham&lt;/a&gt; might fall in that category. She seems notable to me, but there’s only a limited amount of press on her. I also learned a little too late that journalists often do not count as notable, because &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Notability_(journalists)&quot;&gt;Wikipedia has not accepted a specific notability standard for them&lt;/a&gt;. So, people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Sisi_Wei&quot;&gt;Sisi Wei&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Ryann_Jones&quot;&gt;Ryann Jones&lt;/a&gt; might fail to meet the standard, even though there is quite a bit of material on the web about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 20 or so articles my students undertook, seven of them are now live on Wikipedia. I’ll admit to being a little confused about how articles end up in the main namespace– some things that I’ve written have just ended up there right away, while others get stuck with an “awaiting review” flag, and others are just in the draft namespace with no such tag. Oliver Keyes and Mikhail Popov offered me some guidance on the Friendly Tech Space Slack (it lives up to its name!) and the most recent conclusion is that I conincidentally had students do this assignment during an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Autoconfirmed_article_creation_trial/Post-trial_Research_Report&quot;&gt;Autoconfirmed article creation trial&lt;/a&gt; at Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those seven articles are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynn_Cherny&quot;&gt;Lynn Cherny&lt;/a&gt; (saved from deletion from a friendly editor with a female-sounding username)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janaya_Khan&quot;&gt;Janaya Khan&lt;/a&gt; (probably the best article to come out of this class, and one of the names the students came up with themselves!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffrey_T._Leek&quot;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgia_Lupi&quot;&gt;Giorgia Lupi&lt;/a&gt; (may not actually have been reviewed yet, perhaps I just dropped it into the main namespace?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefanie_Posavec&quot;&gt;Stefanie Posavec&lt;/a&gt; (also may not have been reviewed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria_Stodden&quot;&gt;Victoria Stodden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jer_Thorp&quot;&gt;Jer Thorp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think those articles are fantastic, and I’m glad to see them added to Wikipedia! But, that means the vast majority of the articles my students wrote are either waiting for review, or have been rejected. The queue of articles waiting for review is long, and the flag says they are “reviewed in no specific order” but that it may take 8 weeks or more to get a review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have enough data here to back this up, but it seems that of the articles my students wrote that have already been reviewed, the ones about men (Jeff Leek and Jer Thorp) were reviewed quickly, given the benefit of the doubt (see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeffrey_T._Leek&amp;amp;diff=828628510&amp;amp;oldid=824547453&quot;&gt;charitable comments on the article about Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;, even though the draft might not have been of the highest quality), and accepted. The ones about women are either still waiting to be reviewed, or have been rejected on grounds that I think are pretty weak (see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Amanda_Cox&quot;&gt;comment on the article about Amanda Cox&lt;/a&gt; that rejects her article because it says she served on the Federal Reserve Board, rather than that she worked at the Fed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the rejections that are getting me particularly riled up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Jennifer_(Jenny)_Bryan&quot;&gt;Jenny Bryan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Amanda_Cox&quot;&gt;Amanda Cox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Kim_Rees&quot;&gt;Kim Rees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Julia_Silge&quot;&gt;Julia Silge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think those people (women) are extremely notable, and we should work to get their pages up to snuff. Will you help me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another place you could jump in is trying to improve the articles we have that are still in the review queue (or that I’ve re-submitted after rejection), to hopefully forestall any issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Kennedy_Elliott&quot;&gt;Kennedy Elliot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Meredith_Broussard&quot;&gt;Meredith Broussard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Beatrice_Fischel-Bock&quot;&gt;Beatrice Fischel-Bock&lt;/a&gt; (another student-generated idea!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Lena_Groeger&quot;&gt;Lena Groeger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Mark_Hansen&quot;&gt;Mark Hansen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Sisi_Wei&quot;&gt;Sisi Wei&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Charlotte_Wickham&quot;&gt;Charlotte Wickham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if you’re looking for folks to write articles about, I’m giving away ideas for free! How about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mara Averick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nadieh Bremer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karl Broman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jen Christiansen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jessica Hullman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michelle Minkoff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hilary Parker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olga Pierce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Robinson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irene Ros&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kara Woo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nathan Yau&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/03/20/Wikipedia-in-the-classroom.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/03/20/Wikipedia-in-the-classroom.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/Jenny_wikipedia.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Dagstuhl reflections</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last 10 days, I had the pleasure of attending &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rstudio.com/conference/&quot;&gt;rstudio::conf&lt;/a&gt; and the Dagstuhl seminar on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dagstuhl.de/en/program/calendar/semhp/?semnr=18061&quot;&gt;Evidence about Programmers for Programming Language Design&lt;/a&gt;. At rstudio::conf, I taught a two-day workshop on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/IntroToR&quot;&gt;Intro to R &amp;amp; RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, and at the Dagstuhl I mostly thought about exposing novices to programming in scientific contexts. So, there was a lot of overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://www.dagstuhl.de/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/Dagstuhl.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Schloss Dagstuhl&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dagstuhl.de/&quot;&gt;Schloss Dagstuhl&lt;/a&gt; is a historic castle that hosts workshops on topics related to computer science. The idea is to bring a small group of people (ours was about 35) together for a week to discuss a specific topic, with the goal of advancing the discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, what we wanted to advance was evidence about programmers for programming language design. Most programming languages are designed by intuition. But, given that the people who write programming languages are not always the people who use them, and we may be quite different from most users, this is likely not the best strategy. To improve, we’d like to put the “science” in “computer science.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began the week with presentations from a subset of the attendees (I wrote a separate post about my talk, &lt;a href=&quot;www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html&quot;&gt;Scientists Programming&lt;/a&gt;). The talks were aimed to ground us in the disparate disciplines we came from, including programming language design, eye tracking, science, and education. Then, we spent the remainder of the time in discussion, both small-group and full-group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was invited to the workshop by &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.cs.unlv.edu/stefika/&quot;&gt;Andreas Stefik&lt;/a&gt;, the absolute master of Skype networking with other academics. Stefik is known for developing an evidence-based programming language, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://quorumlanguage.com/&quot;&gt;Quorum&lt;/a&gt;. He was the only person I had interacted with at all before the conference, and our interactions had been limited to Skype and email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I discovered many connections with other folks once I was there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brad-meyers---better-language-goals&quot;&gt;Brad Meyers - better language goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first presentations of the workshop was by Brad Myers, who &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.BradA.Myers1.Slides1.pdf&quot;&gt;spoke about&lt;/a&gt; types of studies. However, what stuck out the most to me was his modified version of programming language goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Brad Myers started his &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/dagstuhl?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#dagstuhl&lt;/a&gt; talk by comparing programming language design goals:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(traditional)&lt;br /&gt;1. Correctness&lt;br /&gt;2. Performance (of code)&lt;br /&gt;3. Expressiveness&lt;br /&gt;4. Speed of compiling &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(usability)&lt;br /&gt;5. Understandability &lt;br /&gt;6. Ease of reading&lt;br /&gt;7. Modifiability&lt;br /&gt;8. Learnability&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/960502906821767168?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These goals reminded me of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1610.00985&quot;&gt;key attributes for a modern statistical programming tool&lt;/a&gt; paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neil-brown---data-on-student-errors&quot;&gt;Neil Brown - data on student errors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Brown, who worked on Greenfoot and BlueJ (IDEs for novices learning Java) was there. He and I talked about a principle I have absorbed from Greenfoot, that novices should never be presented with a blank screen, but instead some scaffolding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown has data on many students’ Java code from Blackbox, a way to capture data from students using BlueJ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Next up, Neil Brown of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KingsCollegeLon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@KingsCollegeLon&lt;/a&gt; on analyzing programming data. BlueJay is an IDE for Java beginners, Blackbox can capture data about it. They have data on 300 million compilations, which is &lt;br /&gt;~3TB (compressed) of source code.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961530821596401664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teachers think they are good at predicting errors, but they actually are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Teachers are pretty certain they can predict what errors students will make. But, is that actually true?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961533231077175296?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This and many other great insights are in &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.NeilC.C.Brown1.Slides.pdf&quot;&gt;Brown’s slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brett-becker---better-errors&quot;&gt;Brett Becker - better errors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of errors, Brett Becker &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.BrettA.Becker2.Slides.pdf&quot;&gt;talked about&lt;/a&gt; improving compiler errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Becker: Error messages are accusatory and negative. Do we need to say “terminated” and “illegal”? “I’m going to get killed, and I’m going to jail.”&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961546402986897410?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;felienne---what-is-programming&quot;&gt;Felienne - what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; programming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to meet &lt;a href=&quot;http://felienne.com/&quot;&gt;Felienne&lt;/a&gt; in person after hearing Jenny Bryan &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jennybc/2016-06_spreadsheets&quot;&gt;talk about her&lt;/a&gt;, and following her on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/felienne&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; for years. Felienne gave my favorite &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.FelienneHermans1.Slides.key&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; of the workshop, which ranged from her work on spreadsheets as programming to her more recent work teaching students about “code smells” in Scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felienne asked “What is programming anyway?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;What is programming anyway? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; talking about 🧠head vs. ❤️. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/9qCfMq80KW&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9qCfMq80KW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961151780657729537?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She pointed out that while “every programmer ever” says that “Everyone should learn programming,” the community can be quite restrictive about what it considers to be “real programming.” Funnily enough, while everyone seemed to understand what she was saying, I also got pushback about &lt;a href=&quot;www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html&quot;&gt;my talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, we put users in one category and programmers in the other. But, there are many people who are “swimming in the water” of programming, and don’t even know they’re doing it. People who work deeply with spreadsheets are programmers, but they wouldn’t describe themselves that way. Again, this had reverberations with the &lt;a href=&quot;www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html&quot;&gt;scientists programming&lt;/a&gt; stuff I talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;After spreadsheets, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; started working on “code smells” in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scratch?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@scratch&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Ci9hGnesSh&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Ci9hGnesSh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961153216971931648?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felienne asked us two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Two dimensions: what is programming for? What is programming like? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; making a case for creativity and self-expression. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/GzzSRg5Rc0&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/GzzSRg5Rc0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961156021279444992?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One answer to “what is programming like?” is writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;One metaphor &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; likes is programming as writing. There are many things that “count” as writing. Can be for yourself, can be for others, can be creative. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/eMlZhaJQ2D&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/eMlZhaJQ2D&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961159455948886016?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used it a lot, so I think programming as writing is a pretty robust metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baker-franke---teachability-and-learnability&quot;&gt;Baker Franke - teachability and learnability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another person I was delighted to meet was &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke&quot;&gt;Baker Franke&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.org/&quot;&gt;code.org&lt;/a&gt;, who it turns out worked on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://exploringcs.org/&quot;&gt;Exploring Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; (ECS) project before I joined it as a graduate student. At some point, I used the phrase “data the students can see themselves in” and he mentioned he’d written something about that in the early ECS curriculum. I’m now certain that’s where this idea (which I have fully integrated into my worldview) came from. It’s always fun to pin down those influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franke’s talk was also great, and teased out the subtle differences between learnability and teachability of a language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;We’ve been expanding our definition of language properties at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/dagstuhl?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#dagstuhl&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bakerfranke&lt;/a&gt; adding “teachability,” although he says this might not be a problem for language designers but a problem of pedagogy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/b1HlrgUJyH&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/b1HlrgUJyH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961185848539713538?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He echoed my feeling that consistency in teaching is so important (the reason why I teach only one R syntax in my intro classes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;For learners, consistency is good. Flexibility may not be helpful. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bakerfranke&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/g8NokrqC15&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/g8NokrqC15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961187475308863490?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has an idea about scaffolding in language design,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Mitch Resnik wanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scratch?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@scratch&lt;/a&gt; to have a low floor, high ceiling, wise walls. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bakerfranke&lt;/a&gt; wants a low floor, high ceiling, narrow walls to start, and wider walls as you get closer to the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961192913714675713?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was just a selection of the talks that related most directly to my interests. If you want to see the rest of them, they are posted on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/index.php?semnr=18061&quot;&gt;seminar materials page&lt;/a&gt;, and for more context on the people who attended (not all of whom presented), you can read &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.SWM.Slides.pdf&quot;&gt;everyone’s introductory slide&lt;/a&gt;, and check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/lists/evidenceaboutprogrammers&quot;&gt;twitter list&lt;/a&gt; I made of all the participants who are on twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-than-talks&quot;&gt;More than talks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course the point of the Dagstuhl was not just talks. It was making connections with other researchers. At every meal, we were assigned random seats to help us meet more people. We had structured time to think about programming language design studies we would like to see (thanks, Baker!) and time to discuss in groups. At the end of the last day, we developed a massive spreadsheet of current projects, future projects, and resources. I can see at least five potential projects I might lead or become involved with. The types of things I think about in terms of teaching statistics and R seemed to fit right in with the questions others at the workshop were asking– a novel feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I’m not the only one who feels this way. Several other folks have already written up their thoughts on the seminar, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/bits-and-behavior/designing-learnable-teachable-and-productive-programming-languages-dagstuhl-trip-report-81e41bde84bd&quot;&gt;Andy Ko&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cszero.wordpress.com/2018/02/11/dagstuhl-seminar-18061-evidence-about-programmers-for-programming-language-design/&quot;&gt;Brett Becker&lt;/a&gt;, and of course &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.felienne.com/archives/tag/dagstuhl&quot;&gt;Felienne’s liveblogging&lt;/a&gt;. 
Johannes Hofmeister captured his ideas on video,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-partner=&quot;tweetdeck&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Me, trying to capture all my ideas from the Dagstuhl seminar. Not a time lapse, actual speed of thoughts :D &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/kDolr7e8gb&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/kDolr7e8gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Johannes Hofmeister (@pro_cessor) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pro_cessor/status/962765672110592000?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t wait to see where things go from here.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 05:43:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Dagstuhl-reflections.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Dagstuhl-reflections.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/Dagstuhl.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>More guys</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One incidental piece of the Dagstuhl is I thought more about the use of the term “guys.” While we were going around and doing our initial 3-minute introductions, I heard a lot of uses of “guys” that rubbed me the wrong way, so when I introduced myself I asked people to think about their gendered word choices throughout the seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regret doing this, because I think it marked me as someone who cares mainly about gender issues (I was there for the PL design stuff!) and I don’t think anyone really understood my point. People did become more aware of when they were saying it (and we used “squirrels!” as an interjection when someone did it), but not in a way that fostered inclusiveness. I’ll try to outline my personal opinion on the term here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/27/guys-guys-guys/&quot;&gt;the results&lt;/a&gt; from the survey I linked in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2017/12/19/On-Microaggressions.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I find it gender-neutral when people use the second person phrasing of “you guys.” This means it’s okay to address a mixed-gender group by saying “hey guys, what’s up?” “okay guys, let’s focus” “it’s time for us to go to lunch, guys,” etc. (That being said, I would encourage you to work toward saying something more inclusive, like “folks”, “peeps”, “ya’ll”, “everyone”, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem comes when you talk about people in the third person. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/27/guys-guys-guys/&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt;, phrases like “we’re going to need to hire a Python guy” or “I met a great Erlang guy” were perceived by the majority &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be gender-neutral. This is the useage that people were abusing in the Dagstuhl. I often heard people say, “I was talking to the google guys,” “I know the guys who worked on that,” “the guys who study these things,” etc. If the speaker realized they had used the word guys, they would justify by saying “and they’re actually all men,” as if that made it okay. That is actually &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a rule of thumb, I told someone at the Dagstuhl “if you can see the people in front of you, saying “guys” is okay. If you can’t see them, don’t use it.” This is perhaps an oversimplication, but it gets at that second-person (“you guys”) versus third-person (“those guys”) distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that women are underrepresented in STEM, and perhaps particularly in computer science (the Dagstuhl seminar I attended was about 20% female, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961900236477169664&quot;&gt;seems to be the norm&lt;/a&gt;). Ed Yong outlines some of the issues in the beginning of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/02/i-spent-two-years-trying-to-fix-the-gender-imbalance-in-my-stories/552404/&quot;&gt;piece on increasing the diversity of scientists he quotes&lt;/a&gt;. To quote Ed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Women in science face a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/03/the-5-biases-pushing-women-out-of-stem&quot;&gt;gauntlet of well-documented systemic biases&lt;/a&gt;. They face long-standing stereotypes about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/01/six-year-old-girls-already-have-gendered-beliefs-about-intelligence/514340/&quot;&gt;their intelligence&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/scitable/content/does-gender-matter-by-ben-a-barres-10602856&quot;&gt;scientific acumen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2016/02/male-biology-students-underestimate-their-female-peers/462924/&quot;&gt;They need better college grades&lt;/a&gt; to get the same prestige as equally skilled men, they &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/109/41/16474.full&quot;&gt;receive less mentoring&lt;/a&gt;, they’re rated as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/109/41/16474.full&quot;&gt;less competent and less employable&lt;/a&gt; than equally qualified men, they’re less likely to be invited to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/12/women-are-invited-to-give-fewer-talks-than-men-at-top-us-universities/548657/&quot;&gt;give talks&lt;/a&gt;, they earn &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/inequality-quantified-mind-the-gender-gap-1.12550&quot;&gt;less than their male peers&lt;/a&gt;, and they have to deal with significant levels of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/context-and-variation/safe13-field-site-chilly-climate-and-abuse/&quot;&gt;harassment and abuse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you say “the guys at google,” you are erasing the women who work there, even if the people &lt;em&gt;you happen to know&lt;/em&gt; are all male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know lots of cool men, but when I talk about teams to my students (who are mostly female, because I work at a women’s college) I try to speak in gender neutral terms. If my students have heard me talk about “the people I know at google,” “the people I know at facebook,” “the people who work on the tidyverse,” etc., they can project themselves into that group. When they come to me for a contact at a company, and I put them in touch with a man, that feels incidental. I know lots of people, that contact just happened to be male. Plus, in between when I make those statements in class and when people follow up, teams often diversify and I meet more folks. So by starting with a gender-neutral, I’m leaving the door open for more diverse teams in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to hear about gender, I want to hear about the work. If you are going to reference a specific person, of course it is okay to indicate their gender and use their pronouns. But, if you’re going to speak about a group of two or more people in the third person, please try to remove the word “guys” from your vocabulary. We’re all people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://prestosketching.com/blog/2018/01/27/easy-ways-to-show-more-diversity-in-your-sketches/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/faces-hair.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Many diverse face sketches&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Image via &lt;a href=&quot;http://prestosketching.com/blog/2018/01/27/easy-ways-to-show-more-diversity-in-your-sketches/&quot;&gt;prestosketching&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 04:53:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/More-guys.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/More-guys.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/faces-hair.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Scientists Programming</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At the Dagstuhl seminar, &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.cs.unlv.edu/stefika/&quot;&gt;Andreas Stefik&lt;/a&gt; asked me to speak about “Scientists Programming.” I’m not sure whether he did this on purpose, but by assigning people their talk titles, he drew us a little outside our comfort zone and got us to think more deeply. “Scientists Programming” wasn’t a talk that I had in my pocket, and wasn’t what I would have proposed, but it was fun to pull together. It made me realize that scientists programming is actually one of my primary interests, although I’ve never written that anywhere before. Felienne wrote up a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.felienne.com/archives/5900&quot;&gt;nice summary&lt;/a&gt; of my talk, but I wanted to write down some thoughts of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/clement127/15236140202/in/photolist-pdncEs-rabMJr-qSKYvp-qPeSji-rmJJdW-btryhH-qK7VJj-cm1Hb-qdaYpW-fWAdZ-9WhgHt-oLa2TT-2vuJD-2vuKd-mk1ib-qAU7wq-r3voVM-8CAcWc-9oggZ-7w3hnt-56tdL-oLa3fV-2vuPq-2vuJ5-oLqNAT-otW1FH-hGxPy-9Gbfpi-kyh6Q-wL7Y9q-anxVft-otW5n1-bWGa2P-qmxh8-otWG7V-nCpBGK-oLa2C2-pqcggk-61RzgT-dgrA8g-gbGJp-nBBqqg-anxVyP-6KVaRB-anAxnS-anxJWP-oJoZ4d-rcEdVP-aySHmX-anxJdr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/ScientistsProgramming.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Female lego scientist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the talk, I broke scientists’ programming tasks three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making models to generate data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generating data to make models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;application programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That first category would include any scientist who has a theory about the world, and using modeling to try to represent some relationship, then runs the model to generate data. Once you have that data, you compare it to what you’ve seen in the real world to see how good your model is. I’ve seen this done in ecology with predator/prey relationships, but I’m pretty sure physicists, chemists, and many others use this same technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second category is the one I think about the most, because it’s more statistical. In this paradigm, scientists generate data (through experimentation, surveying, observation, etc), and use those data to generate a model, which is likely statistical. Then, they assess how well the model does at representing the real world. I see these first two paradigms as two sides of the same coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final category, application programming, is the one I know the least about. I know some scientists do things like program a Raspberry Pi to do some specific sensor activity, or program a robot to explore in a deep cave. However, I think that this category is usually in service of one of the above two (scientists are usually trying to observe something about the world). Since application programming is outside of my expertise, and I knew it would be the most familiar to the group at the Dagstuhl, I didn’t discuss this in my talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.AmeliaA.McNamara1.Slides2.pdf&quot;&gt;see my slides&lt;/a&gt; if you want to know everything I covered, but the meat of the talk was digging into the paper by Julia Stewart Lowndes, et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-017-0160&quot;&gt;“Our path to better science in less time using open data science tools”&lt;/a&gt;. This paper is a perfect case study of a group of scientists who “We thought [they] were doing reproducible science” by using Excel, writing up their process, keeping versions of files by changing filenames, etc. But, they were able to transition to a more robust workflow using git/GitHub, R/RStudio, and RMarkdown. This has made them more accurate, and reduced the amount of time they spend on analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is crucial. Science is the source of a lot of the “ground truth” we rely on as a society. It determines which treatments get used by doctors, what interventions we try on the environment, and just our general knowledge of how the world works. If science is wrong, there are big implications. One common example are &lt;a href=&quot;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-016-1044-7&quot;&gt;Excel errors in genomics research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love that Lowndes’ group has made their code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OHI-Science/&quot;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. This is useful on so many levels&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone wanting to check their calculations can do so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are a scientist, you can use it as a reference for coding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming language designers can examine how scientists authentically code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my talk, I showed some arbitrarily-chosen code from their repo to display how the tidyverse syntax makes code more human-readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_indicator_mean_loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_indicator_mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;left_join&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
                                    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;monitoring_area&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;station_cleaned&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DECWGSN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                           &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DECWGSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 31&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;64.207281&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 30&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;61.679815&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 29&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;59.705518&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 32&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;60.108130&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Rectangle 23 &amp;amp; 28&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;63.505817&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 		&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                           &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 31&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;23.511161&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 30&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;21.269112&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 29&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;21.264879&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 32&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;25.772410&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                                 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Rectangle 23 &amp;amp; 28&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;21.351243&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
                                 		&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;as.character&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                           &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;as.character&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;temp_long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_scores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_area&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;core_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;taxa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;group_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_area&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;core_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;taxa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gather&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ungroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;group_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;basin_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;core_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope_mean_basin_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope_mean_basin_taxa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ungroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;basin_n_obs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_scores_long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
                            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;score1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
                            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Basin_HOLAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
                            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Basin_HOLAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the programming language designers found this code hard to read and confusing. Although I’ve heard computer scientists complain about R many times before, I wasn’t anticipating this. I thought that the piped sequence of function calls would be pretty readable. Maybe it was the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/code&gt; for the pipe rather than &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;, or maybe they would have preferred to see it as separate steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had shown this example, taken from Garrett Grolemund’s Master the Tidyverse materials (which I also showed in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/IntroToR&quot;&gt;Intro to R &amp;amp; RStudio&lt;/a&gt; workshop).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; 
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think with this comparison, it’s easier to see why the piped approach is better for people. With the nested function calls, you have to do a lot of checking in your head to make sure the parentheses are matched, and it’s hard to follow the logic. The incremental approach is good, but you type the name of the data many times. In the last example, the data flows through the piped sequence in a clearer way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question that came up in my talk was “if we fixed the problems with R as a language, would you appreciate that?” and I didn’t have a great answer. As a user, I (and I believe most scientists) don’t feel the language issues that frustrate computer scientists. It just works for what I need to do. In fact, my talk introduced yet another idea that we came back to again and again– some people who use programming languages don’t think of themselves as programmers. I know many people who use R, but consider it a tool to do data analysis rather than something to program in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the thing I exposed people to that they were most excited about was RMarkdown. While it seemed most people were familiar with the idea of iPython/Jupyter notebooks, they hadn’t seen knitr before. The idea that they could create a fully reproducible journal article interweaving text and code was very appealling. I showed a simple example with HTML output including text, code, and code output, but over the next few days I demoed more complex (Rnw) examples from my own work that produce publication-ready documents. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/COSTDataExpo2013/AmeliaMN/blob/master/PaperFinalDraft.pdf&quot;&gt;this pdf of a paper for Computational Statistics&lt;/a&gt; was generated from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/COSTDataExpo2013/AmeliaMN/blob/master/PaperFinalDraft.Rnw&quot;&gt;this LaTeX/knitr file&lt;/a&gt;. While this group of computer scientists work on experiments surrounding programming language design, and therefore do the same types of data analytic tasks as many scientists, they didn’t have this piece of their workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 03:43:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/ScientistsProgramming.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>R syntax comparison</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;For my rstudio::conf working, Intro to R &amp;amp; RStudio, I finally finished my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rstudio/cheatsheets/raw/master/syntax.pdf&quot;&gt;cheatsheet on R syntaxes&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been working on this for at least a year (😱 ), so I’m glad to see it out in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I posted the cheatsheet online, I got some critical feedback, which I would like to address in the form of a FAQ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/rstudio/cheatsheets/raw/master/syntax.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/SyntaxComparisonCheatsheet.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;R syntax comparison cheatsheet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why didn’t you include data.table syntax?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Mostly, because I don’t know &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data.table&lt;/code&gt;, so I wouldn’t have done a good job. Also, because I don’t know of anyone who is teaching data.table to absolute novices. However, if someone wanted to generate all the analogous tasks (summary statistics, plots, wrangling) in data.table and share them, I would be very interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why did you use the word “syntax” when that’s not quite precise?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Because that is a word commonly associated with programming languages. While these three paradigms may not be precisely three different syntaxes, they are certainly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syntactic_sugar&quot;&gt;syntactic sugar&lt;/a&gt; or idioms within the language. I often refer to them as like accents within a human language. If you were learning English, you wouldn’t try to learn it with a British accent, an accent from the American South, and an accent from Australia. You’d learn it one way, and be able to recognize other accents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why didn’t you express [x] in this more efficient way?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; This usually comes up because of my use of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tapply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;efficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;if_else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;TRUE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;FALSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;efficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;if_else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both of these cases, I was erring on the side of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a) more verbosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;b) a more general pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, although I learned R long before the tidyverse existed, I never got adept at the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apply()&lt;/code&gt; family of functions. Every time I needed to use one, it was a fall down a rabbithole of “tapply? sapply? mapply?” (In fact, trying to create that tapply call for this post included just such a search.) While I would encourage people coding within the base R paradigm to learn these functions, I think the three-line version is easier to think through, and represents a much more common “style” that you will see on places like StackOverflow. In many cases, there is no &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; equivalent, and you end up doing this sort of repetitive writing of the dataset name and nesting of statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mutate()&lt;/code&gt; call, even though it was unnecessary to include the TRUE and FALSE, I knew that it would provide a better pattern for students who wanted to make their own variables. If you want &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;efficient&lt;/code&gt; to instead be “yes” and “no” character strings, you can just sub “yes” for TRUE and “no” for FALSE, without having to think about the magic that goes with logicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why didn’t you show ggformula or the formula-based base R plots?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; I did! They’re just on the back of the sheet. I don’t feel like &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ggformula/index.html&quot;&gt;ggformula&lt;/a&gt; is a full-fledged graphics library yet, so I don’t want to present it as such. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;base&lt;/code&gt; graphics, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lattice&lt;/code&gt; graphics and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; graphics are all full libraries, so I used those on the front of the sheet. As for formula-based base R plots, I think they are much less common online. My main use case for this cheatsheet is to give to students who I am teaching one particular syntax. For example, I used to teach completely in the formula syntax, but have switched to tidyverse syntax. However, sometimes when I demo code I switch to another syntax because it feels more natural for the task. Or, students google something and find code from another syntax. The cheatsheet serves as a grounding device to say, this is just another way to express the same idea I am familiar with. Since I (almost) never teach base R, I include it on the cheatsheet mostly as a foil to my argument that the tidyverse is more human-readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have other questions? Ask me in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 02:43:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/02/11/Syntax-comparison.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/02/11/Syntax-comparison.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/SyntaxComparisonCheatsheet.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>On microaggressions</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was glad to see Karl Broman’s blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/12/18/these-guys/&quot;&gt;a troubling conference talk&lt;/a&gt;. In the post, Karl describes how the speaker repeatedly used the word “guys” to describe people involved in statistics, and how he and Hadley Wickham reached out to him in an effort to get him to change his ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were in the room during the talk, I’m sure the experience is still viscerally available to you, but for those who were not, I think Karl’s post falls far short of the necessary description to underscore the problem. As I said in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/942962475418505216&quot;&gt;recent tweet&lt;/a&gt;, it’s hard to convey in words how icky the talk was. But, I’m going to make an attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk was part of a session &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2016/onlineprogram/ActivityDetails.cfm?SessionID=212769&quot;&gt;honoring Bill Cleveland&lt;/a&gt;. Other talks in the session were fantastic– in particular, Di Cook’s talk, where she &lt;a href=&quot;http://visiphilia.org/2016/08/03/CM-hierarchy&quot;&gt;replicated Cleveland and McGill’s findings live&lt;/a&gt; (!!). But this particular speaker, who has now &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-12-16/google-researcher-accused-of-sexual-harassment-roiling-ai-field&quot;&gt;come under scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@kristianlum/statistics-we-have-a-problem-304638dc5de5&quot;&gt;sexual harassment&lt;/a&gt;, gave a talk that was broadly derisive and dismissive of anyone who is not a white man pursuing statistics. I have a record of many of the comments he made as part of email threads from the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a talk that included “data science” in the title, he was dismissive of data science, making the comparison that statistics is like architecture (accompanied by a photo of the Sydney Opera House) while data science is like cookie-cutter tract housing (accompanied by a photo of a suburban development), managing to be derisive of both manual labor and the efforts of many of the people in the audience.  He disparaged useR, saying that you should only go if you want to hear about “guys who made a nice plot.” The entire tenor of the talk was that work with data is less important than statistics, a completely bizarre take in a talk supposedly honoring Bill Cleveland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, the speaker made it clear by his references, language, and tone, that he only considers contributions by men. Every researcher he mentioned by name was male (even though he was speaking shortly after Di Cook, clearly eminent in the field). This might seem like a justification for his gendered language, but I think it speaks to a deeper issue– he simply does not see contributions by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious indicator of his dismissal of women was his repetitive use of the word “guys,” as Karl has mentioned. The usage become more and more grating throughout the talk, but even on his first use of the word the colleague sitting to my left said “sexist” under her breath at the same time I corrected “people” under mine. On twitter, many people chimed in to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/760881386651848708&quot;&gt;Karl’s tweet at the time&lt;/a&gt; saying they found the comments jarring as well. In situations where he could easily have said “people,” “statisticians,” “data scientists,” “programmers,” or many other gender-neutral terms, the speaker always used the word “guys.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes this difficult to adequately describe is that in some contexts, “guys” is almost gender-neutral. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/27/guys-guys-guys/&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidjayharris/status/760933065950629888&quot;&gt;Dave Harris linked&lt;/a&gt; suggests that “guys” is only gender-neutral if you say “you guys.” Phrases like “we’re going to need to hire a Python guy” or “I met a great Erlang guy” were perceived by the majority &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be gender-neutral. As Karl responded to someone saying she didn’t care about the use of “guys” as long as she was not excluded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;in this context, you would have cared.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Karl Broman (@kwbroman) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/760922466894114816?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what is so insidious about these types of microaggressions. When you try to describe them, they sound insignificant, even though for those who were present it was clear there was a pattern of dismissal. It was so blatant that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;steam was literally coming out of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@AmeliaMN&lt;/a&gt;’s ears&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Hadley Wickham (@hadleywickham) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hadleywickham/status/760882186551697409?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’m _still_ shaking with rage. Literally.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Karl Broman (@kwbroman) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/760885433941319680?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, it was clear that some action needed to be taken. Through email, Karl, Hadley, Hilary Parker (looped in for her interest in the issue, although she wasn’t present at the talk) and I discussed that while the talk offended us personally, it wasn’t a clear-cut violation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2016/conductpolicy.cfm&quot;&gt;JSM’s Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt;. This left making a comment to him, either publicly or privately. I knew that I (as a junior, female, data science-y person) would get no respect from him, so I encouraged Karl and Hadley to call him out. The speaker had mentioned Hadley in his talk, and since both of them are more senior, male, and ASA Fellows, I hoped their words would carry some weight. Karl, Hadley, Hilary and I went back and forth via email working on drafts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, we ended up softening the language in successive drafts. A first draft said people “were taken aback, to the point of being offended,” while the final version just says “were taken aback.” Karl initially mentioned that he “might also talk about the pedestrian carpenter data scientist vs the soaring architect applied statistician, but two criticisms without any positive comments seems too much.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a week, the email Karl &lt;a href=&quot;http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/12/18/these-guys/&quot;&gt;reproduced on his blog&lt;/a&gt; was sent, and after a couple months I followed up with Karl to see if the speaker had responded. He hadn’t, and we dropped the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regret that I didn’t feel comfortable writing publicly about this at the time, and that I didn’t push harder for follow-up when I heard he had ignored the email. We now know this particular person has a (alleged) history of sexual harassment, and perhaps publicizing this talk would have opened the issue up earlier. As Mara tweeted,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Reason number 247 &amp;quot;just send an email, we&amp;#39;re all adults here&amp;quot; is operationally disastrous advice. Also, and a whole host of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RLadiesGlobal?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@RLadiesGlobal&lt;/a&gt; can back me up on this, sometimes communicating privately is the OPPOSITE of a good idea!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mara Averick (@dataandme) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dataandme/status/943085039897718785?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 19, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the #metoo movement in general and the recent attention on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@kristianlum/statistics-we-have-a-problem-304638dc5de5&quot;&gt;harassment in statistics, data science, and machine learning&lt;/a&gt; in particular, I am reminded of the Brandeis quote that “Sunlight is said to be the best of disinfectants.” Of course, this is only true if people believe the stories that are voiced, but we seem to be at a watershed moment. I regret not shining more light on this at the time, and hope that we can be more open about violations of community norms, even if they seem “minor.” They could be indicative of a larger pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2017/12/19/On-Microaggressions.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2017/12/19/On-Microaggressions.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/grr.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>What are the chances my name is Amanda?</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I get called Amanda a lot. This tends to drive me crazy, because I think
my real name is much more interesting. But, I realized recently that
given the prior probabilities, it’s actually a very reasonable thing to
call me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Note: this blog post has some interactive elements, so it is probably more fun to read on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ameliamn.shinyapps.io/Amanda/&quot;&gt;my shiny server&lt;/a&gt;. And of course, if you want to see what I did, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/shiny-server/blob/master/Amanda/Amanda.Rmd&quot;&gt;code is on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To investigate this using data, I am using the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/code&gt; R package,
which has data from the Social Security Administration. It includes all
names that had at least 5 uses for a particular gender in a given year.
Obviously, that leaves some people out, but actually this data includes
most (documented) people in the United States. For more about this, see
my data appendix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is to take my (approximate) age and see how likely it is
that my name is Amanda. I look incredibly young, but given that I have a
PhD and am a statistics professor, there’s a lower bound on how young I
could really be. Lets assume that people talking to me believe I was
born between &lt;strong&gt;1980-1989&lt;/strong&gt;, inclusive. So the question is, given that I
was born then, &lt;strong&gt;what are the chances my name is Amanda?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a blog post at the beginning of last semester,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.stat.duke.edu/~mc301/&quot;&gt;Mine&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://citizen-statistician.org/2016/08/13/a-timely-first-day-of-class-example-for-fall-2016-trump-tweets/&quot;&gt;linked&lt;/a&gt;
to a 538 article from 2014 that approaches the problem from the other
side– &lt;a href=&quot;http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-tell-someones-age-when-all-you-know-is-her-name/&quot;&gt;How to tell someone’s age when all you know is her
name&lt;/a&gt;.
Interestingly, although using this method would help confirm people’s
suspicions that I’m a child (the &lt;em&gt;A&lt;strong&gt;g&lt;/strong&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;|&lt;em&gt;N&lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt;m**e&lt;/em&gt; method would
estimate I’m &lt;a href=&quot;http://rhiever.github.io/name-age-calculator/index.html?Gender=F&amp;amp;Name=Amelia&quot;&gt;about 13 years
old&lt;/a&gt;),
that’s not how people tend to think about names and ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/amelias-1.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Amelias'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, people seem to be taking an approximate age and then just
grabbing a name out of the hat. In other words, they are using the
&lt;em&gt;N&lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt;m&lt;strong&gt;e*|*A&lt;/strong&gt;g**e&lt;/em&gt; method. With that in mind, let’s see how likely
Amanda really is. I’m focusing just on girls names for this analysis,
mostly because Amelia isn’t a common boy’s name (see my data appendix).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eighties, numbers for Amanda and Amelia were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;proportion&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amanda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;369690&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0215329&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;even&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amelia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;9734&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0005670&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed only with the information that I was born between 1985 and 1989,
there’s a &lt;strong&gt;2% chance my name is Amanda&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s actually pretty
incredible! (In contrast, there’s just a 0.05% chance my name is
Amelia.) And, we can figure most people remember at least the first
letter of a name. So, what if we add the fact that my name starts with
an A?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eighties, numbers for Amanda and Amelia (out of all A names) were
as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;proportion&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amanda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.1575295&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;even&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amelia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0041478&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there’s a &lt;strong&gt;15.7% chance my name is Amanda&lt;/strong&gt; (and a 0.4% chance my
name is Amelia). The only A name that was more popular than Amanda in
the eighties was Ashley, which made up 19.5% of the female names
starting with A. Of course, Ashley doesn’t have as similar of a sound to
Amelia as Amanda does. I didn’t go this far, but we could also look at
the names starting with Am– I think this would serve to solidify Amanda
as the much more likely choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for those of you that have felt bad about getting my name wrong in
the past– the data supports you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if doing this analysis has made me feel better about being
called Amanda– for that, I just tell myself &lt;strong&gt;“they’re probably mixing
me up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytco.com/amanda-cox-named-editor-the-upshot/&quot;&gt;Amanda
Cox&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-name&quot;&gt;Your name&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this trend hold up with the name people are always calling you? Are
you a Jacob that always gets called Jason? A Kirstin that gets called
Kristen? (I’m guilty of that one.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This is the part of the post that is responsive, so you probably want to head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://45.55.32.181/shiny/Amanda/&quot;&gt;my shiny server&lt;/a&gt;.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://45.55.32.181/shiny/Amanda/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/ShinyScreenShot.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;You want to go to my server version&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-appendix&quot;&gt;Data appendix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can get off-track when doing analyses, so here are a couple more
thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-full-is-the-data&quot;&gt;How full is the data?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I was worried about was how well the data really represented
the population. Uncommon names are excluded for privacy purposes, and I
thought maybe people were getting more (or less) creative with names
over time. It turns out that may be the case, but only slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/missingdata-1.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Missing data'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Min.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;1st Qu.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;3rd Qu.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Max.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;2.462&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;3.535&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;5.592&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;5.406&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;6.793&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;9.374&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, only 5% of people are missing from the data. That feels
pretty good to me. The article mentioned above, 538 estimated that only
1% of the data was missing, which I’m not sure how they estimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-many-baby-boys-are-named-amelia&quot;&gt;How many baby boys are named Amelia?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer– not many. In 2004, the year with the most male Amelias, 14 baby
boys were named Amelia. Or, someone checked the wrong box on a birth
certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;n&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amelia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creativity-in-naming&quot;&gt;Creativity in naming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there’s a lot deeper I could dig on this analysis. Just by
scrolling through the data I noticed there are many other ways to spell
Amanda, which didn’t get taken into account. (Maybe the creative
spellings of Amelia balance it out.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;proportion&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Aamanda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0000006&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;even&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amamda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;178&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0000104&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amanda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;369690&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0215329&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;even&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amandah&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0000009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;odd&quot;&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;Amannda&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;0.0000013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-is-for-eighties&quot;&gt;A is for eighties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can actually see the eighties pretty clearly when you look at plots
of letters names start with. Girls’ names starting with A had been on
the rise since the 1960s, but you see a local maximum in about 1984 and
then a small decline before continuing to rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/nameletters-1.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Letters over time'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/nameletters-2.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;A over time'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2017/01/13/Amanda.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2017/01/13/Amanda.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/amelias-1.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Census data: A rant</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;As usual toward the end of the semester, my students begin working in earnest on their final projects. And as usual, this results in my selective amnesia about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.census.gov&quot;&gt;census.gov&lt;/a&gt; being ruptured yet again. Looking for a way out, I turned to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/798620977202663424&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; and got some good recommendations. In case it’s useful to other teachers/people, I’ll share my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The tl;dr is that you probably want students to be using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.socialexplorer.com/&quot;&gt;Social Explorer&lt;/a&gt;, but read on for the full rant.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, some motivation. A group of students in my class has found some interesting data at the state level, which they think may be related to demographic characteristics of states, like population, poverty level, education, racial makeup, etc. This is where my amnesia kicks in. “It should be really easy to find data like that!” I say. “Let’s go to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://factfinder.census.gov/&quot;&gt;American FactFinder website&lt;/a&gt; and I’ll show you how it works.” We bumble around on the site for a while, clicking on “Data Main” (a page of screenshots and news) “Data tools and apps” (actually has the link to what we want, but buried among other unrelated things), etc. Finally I manage to find FactFinder main page. We select our geography (states) and dismiss the box that is trying to get us to add yet another geography. We search for “poverty” and voila! …the ugliest dataset you have ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;https://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=ACS_14_5YR_S1701&amp;amp;prodType=table&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/FactFinder.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;An ugly table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always encourage students to work with data programmatically, but even I have to admit that it would be easier to delete columns and add better names in a spreadsheet. The column names are in multiple &lt;em&gt;rows&lt;/em&gt; for crying out loud! Plus, what you would like to be observations (states) are actually variables. I am now imagining the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gather&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;spread&lt;/code&gt; in my future. I want students to understand data cleaning and wrangling, but I don’t want their first experience to be hellish. Even my heart is sinking, thinking about doing this all myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apis&quot;&gt;APIs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so what are the alternatives? The Census does offer an API, so I signed up for an API key and started playing with some R packages recommended by folks on twitter. The most commonly-mentioned package was &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acs&lt;/code&gt; (a CRAN package), although I also heard about &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;acs14lite&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;censusapi&lt;/code&gt; (both on GitHub and installable using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;devtools&lt;/code&gt;). Sadly, none of these packages have vignettes. I’ve been using R for almost 10 years, so yes, I could figure it out from the documentation, but it would take time (which I am short on) and isn’t something I can ask the students I have in this class to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.statschat.org.nz/&quot;&gt;Thomas Lumley&lt;/a&gt; pointed me to this blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://dlab.berkeley.edu/blog/season-sharing-data-working-newly-released-census-2010-2014-acs-5-year-data-r&quot;&gt;working with ACS data in R&lt;/a&gt; which was much more readable. I’m not thinking about maps for this particular application, but I can read around that part. I was able to reproduce the code in the post (yeah!) and modify the first retrieval command to get data for states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stateDemo &amp;lt;- acs14(geography='state', variable = c('B17021_001E'))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, this isn’t the only variable I’m interested in! So, how do I learn what other variables I want? As far as I can tell, I have to go to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://api.census.gov/&quot;&gt;Census API site&lt;/a&gt; and read &lt;a href=&quot;http://api.census.gov/data/2015/acs1/variables.html&quot;&gt;this table&lt;/a&gt;. Say I’m interested in race. I can search the page for that word, but I get almost 5,000 results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/RaceSearch.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Results of searching for `race.'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even if I locate a variable I am interested in, the descriptions are pretty hard to parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/VariableDescription.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Variable description'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of this is that it would be all too easy to think you were getting one thing and actually request another. Plus, when you generate your list of variable strings like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;B02001_009E&lt;/code&gt;, you also need to maintain a corresponding list of human-readable names like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TwoOrMoreCount&lt;/code&gt;. If I were writing a peer-reviewed research paper, I would be grateful for the huge amount of detailed breakdowns and the API access, but for a semester-long student project in a class focused on modeling, it’s too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-my-network&quot;&gt;Using my network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked on Slack, several folks sent me files they had created using the APIs (thanks, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dataandme&quot;&gt;Mara&lt;/a&gt; and Adam!), but of course they didn’t have all the variables I really wanted. And, while I’m grateful to my supportive social media network, I know not everyone has that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-interfaces&quot;&gt;User interfaces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been expecting to be able to find a bunch of GitHub repos full of cleaned up data like the stuff Mara and Adam sent to me on Slack. It seems like people don’t really do that, or if they do it’s not documented in such a way that it is findable. But, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryan_boyer2&quot;&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt; pointed me to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.socialexplorer.com/&quot;&gt;Social Explorer&lt;/a&gt;, an online tool mostly designed for making pretty maps online, that includes a Tables functionality that is almost exactly what I was looking for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://www.socialexplorer.com/tables/C2010&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/SocialExplorer.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Variable description'&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allows you to select your geography, then you can search by keyword or scroll through a manageable list of variable names and add them to a custom table. You can preview the data (it looks like states will be the variables, but never fear, this changes in the download), then choose the format you want to export it in. Other than a slight loss of reproducibility, the only drawback in my mind is that the variable names are still unintelligible, so you have to also download a data dictionary, but it &lt;em&gt;makes you a custom dictionary&lt;/em&gt; based on the variables you chose so you don’t have to wade through the entire thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Tables functionality is mostly for “premium” users, which is too bad, but Smith (like many other academic institutions) has a site license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there other resources out there I have missed? Why is this such a hard problem? I’d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2016/11/16/CensusRant.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2016/11/16/CensusRant.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/FactFinder.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Statistics graduate school advice</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;It’s that time of year again, the time where I find myself meeting with students thinking about graduate school in statistics. Since I often end up sending people the same things, I figured I’d pull them together into a blog post. You probably already know about &lt;a href=&quot;https://thegradcafe.com/&quot;&gt;the grad cafe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://theprofessorisin.com/pearlsofwisdom/&quot;&gt;the professor is in&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php&quot;&gt;PhD comics&lt;/a&gt;. These other links might not be as common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://www.phdcomics.com/comics.php?f=1286&amp;amp;fb_action_ids=148470391984848&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/PhDcomic.gif&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;One of my favorite PhD comics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-is-grad-school-in-statistics-like&quot;&gt;Q: What is grad school in statistics like?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-here-are-some-resources-to-help-you-get-a-taste&quot;&gt;A: Here are some resources to help you get a taste:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When I was still in graduate school, I wrote a three-part blog series for &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la&quot;&gt;datascience.la&lt;/a&gt; on graduate school: &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/statistics-grad-school-what-is-it-really-like/&quot;&gt;Statistics grad school– what is it really like?&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/part-2-of-statistics-grad-school-what-is-it-really-like/&quot;&gt;Part 2 of what statistics grad school is like&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/paying-for-statistics-grad-school-aka-the/&quot;&gt;Part 3: Paying for statistics graduate school&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I gave some additional advice in this recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2016/09/01/inspire/&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt; in AmstatNews.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://statsbylopez.com/about/&quot;&gt;Michael Lopez&lt;/a&gt; also has a piece called &lt;a href=&quot;https://statsbylopez.com/2014/07/23/so-you-want-a-graduate-degree-in-statistics/&quot;&gt;So you want a graduate degree in statistics?&lt;/a&gt;, with sections on deciding on a program, thriving once you are there, and much more. He goes in to the difference between biostatistics and statistics, a PhD and an MA, and how to evaluate programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-where-should-i-go-for-grad-school&quot;&gt;Q: Where should I go for grad school?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-wherever-seems-like-a-good-fit&quot;&gt;A: Wherever seems like a good fit!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really think statistics is such an in-demand field that you can get a job with a degree from virtually any school. These show my personal research interests and biases, but a couple of my favorite programs to recommend to students are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stat.iastate.edu/&quot;&gt;Statistics at Iowa State&lt;/a&gt;. This is where &lt;a href=&quot;http://hadley.nz/&quot;&gt;Hadley Wickham&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://yihui.name/knitr/&quot;&gt;Yihui Xie&lt;/a&gt; got their PhDs, and current students include &lt;a href=&quot;http://cpsievert.github.io/about/&quot;&gt;Carson Sievert&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/maggiejohnsonmn&quot;&gt;Maggie Johnson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://andeekaplan.com/&quot;&gt;Andee Kaplan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sctyner.github.io/&quot;&gt;Samantha Tyner&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://erichare.me/&quot;&gt;Eric Hare&lt;/a&gt;. Notable faculty include &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.public.iastate.edu/~hofmann/&quot;&gt;Hieke Hofmann&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://ugenschel.github.io/&quot;&gt;Ulrike Genschel&lt;/a&gt;. [Update, 11/27/17, I believe &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of those students now have PhDs!]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jhsph.edu/departments/biostatistics/index.html&quot;&gt;Biostatistics at Johns Hopkins&lt;/a&gt;. This is where &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hspter&quot;&gt;Hilary Parker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/acfrazee&quot;&gt;Alyssa Frazee&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jennakrall.com/&quot;&gt;Jenna Krall&lt;/a&gt; got their PhDs. Notable faculty include &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biostat.jhsph.edu/~rpeng/&quot;&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://jtleek.com/&quot;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bcaffo.com/&quot;&gt;Brian Caffo&lt;/a&gt; (of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/jhu-data-science/1&quot;&gt;Coursera data science specialization&lt;/a&gt; fame).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://idl.cs.washington.edu/&quot;&gt;University of Washington Interactive Data Lab&lt;/a&gt;. Not exactly a grad program, because it involves people from both computer science and the school of information, but does awesome work. Notable students include &lt;a href=&quot;http://arvindsatya.com/&quot;&gt;Arvind Satyanarayan&lt;/a&gt; [Update 11/27/17, he has his PhD!], and faculty include &lt;a href=&quot;http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~jheer/&quot;&gt;Jeff Heer&lt;/a&gt; of the computer science department and &lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.washington.edu/jhullman/&quot;&gt;Jessica Hullman&lt;/a&gt; in the iSchool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact I recently learned– Iowa State was the first US university with a department of statistics, and Johns Hopkins the first (in the world?) to offer biostatistics!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-how-do-i-get-in-to-grad-school&quot;&gt;Q: How do I get in to grad school?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-you-need-lots-of-things-to-be-a-strong-candidate-including&quot;&gt;A: You need lots of things to be a strong candidate, including:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good (but not necessarily perfect) grades&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a decent GRE score (particularly on the quantitative section of the regular GRE)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a compelling story in your personal statement (email me if you want to read mine, I don’t feel like posting it on the web)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;solid letters of recommendation, particularly from faculty members who know you well from a variety of contexts, like class, research, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also always recommend reaching out to people from the program you are applying to, whether current grad students, alumni, or professors to get a better sense of a program and whether you would be a good fit. &lt;a href=&quot;http://science-professor.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Female Science Professor&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;http://science-professor.blogspot.com/2011/10/writing-to-me-reprise.html&quot;&gt;a great post&lt;/a&gt; about what to say (and not to say) in an email to a professor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-how-do-i-succeed-in-grad-school&quot;&gt;Q: How do I succeed in grad school?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-i-recommend-the-following&quot;&gt;A: I recommend the following:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://howtoprepforgradschoolwhilepoor.wikispaces.com/&quot;&gt;How to Prep for Grad School if You’re Poor&lt;/a&gt;- a wiki with some information about the application process, but mostly the “cultural capital” you might not have that could be useful when you’re in grad school.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.indiana.edu/how.2b/how.2b.research.html&quot;&gt;Doing research&lt;/a&gt;- how to do research (the short story: do a little every day).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://matt.might.net/articles/advice-for-phd-thesis-proposals/&quot;&gt;A thesis proposal is a contract&lt;/a&gt;. Or at least, it should be.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.jhu.edu/~jason/advice/write-the-paper-first.html&quot;&gt;Write the paper first&lt;/a&gt;- an idea about how to frame your work by writing the paper first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.ucla.edu/~frederic/oralexams.html&quot;&gt;Oral exams&lt;/a&gt;- this is specifically about advancing to candidacy at UCLA in statistics, but I’ve sent it to friends in other programs who don’t have similar guidelines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leek Group Guides to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/reviews&quot;&gt;reviewing papers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/datasharing&quot;&gt;data sharing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/firstpaper&quot;&gt;writing your first paper&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jtleek/readingpapers&quot;&gt;reading papers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-how-can-i-learn-more&quot;&gt;Q: How can I learn more?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-i-recommend-getting-involved-in-some-online-communities&quot;&gt;A: I recommend getting involved in some online communities.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a ton of activity in statistics and data science on twitter. Most of the faculty and students I mentioned above have twitter accounts (some linked above, the others easy to find), and if you are into R you can get a taste by looking at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&quot;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/tidyverse?src=hash&quot;&gt;#tidyverse&lt;/a&gt; hashtags.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roger Peng and Jeff Leek (mentioned above) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://rafalab.github.io/&quot;&gt;Rafa Irizarry&lt;/a&gt; have a blog called &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/&quot;&gt;Simply Statistics&lt;/a&gt; with all sorts of interesting statistics discussions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hilary Parker and Roger Peng (mentioned above) have a podcast called &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/2015/09/17/not-so-standard-deviations-the-podcast/&quot;&gt;Not so standard devations&lt;/a&gt;, available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/nssd-podcast&quot;&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/not-so-standard-deviations/id1040614570?mt=2&quot;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;, and many more podcast distributors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I miss? What are other questions you have?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2016/10/19/GradSchool.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2016/10/19/GradSchool.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/PhDcomic.gif" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Worth adding to your inbox</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;For the most part, I get my data news from the web (blogs like &lt;a href=&quot;http://flowingdata.com/&quot;&gt;flowingdata&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://simplystatistics.org/&quot;&gt;simply statistics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.statschat.org.nz/&quot;&gt;stats chat&lt;/a&gt;) and twitter (check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/following&quot;&gt;people I follow&lt;/a&gt;). However, there are a few email mailing lists I’ve joined that are worth the addional lines in my inbox. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyletter.com/data-is-plural&quot;&gt;Data Is Plural&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jsvine&quot;&gt;Jeremy Singer-Vine&lt;/a&gt;. A great source of open, interesting data sets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyletter.com/abovechart&quot;&gt;Above Chart&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/site/author/scott_klein&quot;&gt;Scott Klein&lt;/a&gt;. Historical data visualizations from newspapers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oreilly.com/data/newsletter.html&quot;&gt;O’Reilly Data Newsletter&lt;/a&gt;. News about data (often skews toward computer science).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2016/06/23/Listservs.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2016/06/23/Listservs.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/InboxZero.png" />
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>