<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
	<channel>
		<title>Amelia McNamara</title>
		<description>Amelia McNamara, assistant professor of statistics in the Department of Computer &amp; Information Sciences at the University of St Thomas</description>		
		<link>https://www.amelia.mn</link>
		<atom:link href="https://www.amelia.mn/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Guidelines I follow when giving talks</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;As with everything in life, there are no hard-and-fast rules for giving talks. But, I have a number of conventions I have developed over the years that I think make for clear(er) presentations. If you look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLik6fAQnSI91PMsa69RJcdKG4L4BiV5MX&quot;&gt;talks I have given&lt;/a&gt; you will see many of these things in practice. I started writing up some of these conventions for my Data Communication course, but realized there might be broader interest, so I’m making it a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/YouTubeTalks.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Videos of talks I&#39;ve given on YouTube&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro-slide&quot;&gt;Intro slide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intro slide should be eye-catching, because it is often up on the screen for longer than everything else. If you’re giving a talk in person, it is sometimes on the screen for several minutes before you actually get up to give your talk, and for the first moments as you begin speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always try to find an engaging image on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/&quot;&gt;flickr&lt;/a&gt; that is Creative Commons licensed. Google Image search also has a filter for CC licensed images, but I find the collection on flickr to be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first image always bleeds across the entire slide. Evergreen Data has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephanieevergreen.com/bleeding-your-presentation/&quot;&gt;nice explanation&lt;/a&gt; of why it’s good to bleed images wherever possible. To make slides look nice in high resolution, I always download the largest possible image from flickr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the image, I put the title of my presentation, my name, and at least one way to contact me (usually my twitter handle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-yourself&quot;&gt;Introducing yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you begin a presentation you are often nervous. I’ve developed a little “patter” I say at the beginning of any talk I give in person. It goes something like this: “I’m Amelia McNamara. I teach at the University of St Thomas in Minnesota, and I tweet at AmeliaMN. That’s a double-entendre, because my last name is McNamara, and I live in Minnesota. I just tweeted a link to these slides, if you want to follow along.” By the time I’ve said that (out of sheer force of habit) usually my nerves have calmed down, and I can begin with my content. (In classes, I find I almost always start with “hi folks! It’s [insert day of the week]” for similar reasons.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slide-content&quot;&gt;Slide content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Edward Tufte so effectively explains in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edwardtufte.com/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg?msg_id=0001yB&quot;&gt;PowerPoint does Rocket Science&lt;/a&gt;, many technical presentations get bogged down by having too much information on the screen at once. I try my best to not include formulas on slides unless absolutely necessary, and reduce the number of words on slides as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want your audience focusing on what you have to say, more than reading what’s behind you. But, the slides should give them something to look at (maybe a pretty picture!) or an overview of the idea. I mostly present at conferences, and attendees like to take photos of slides and live-tweet them, so a slide that stands alone as a summary is a good way to encourage that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like optimizing the data-ink ratio for a data visualization, you can often simplify a slide down to just its most important point by &lt;a href=&quot;http://stephanieevergreen.com/atomic-slide-development/&quot;&gt;iteratively removing information&lt;/a&gt;. If you have an image on a slide, it should probably fill or almost-fill the slide. Same with a data visualization. When I include a ggplot image on a slide, I scale it so the visualization fills as much of the page as possible, often cutting off some of the white margins at the top and bottom. &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephanieevergreen.com/rottemplate/&quot;&gt;The rule of thirds&lt;/a&gt; can make your slides look more professionally-designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evergreen Data has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephanieevergreen.com/top-four-mistakes-seen-in-conference-presentations/&quot;&gt;summary of the top four mistakes seen in conference presentations&lt;/a&gt;. I disagree slightly with some of these mistakes– I tend to include references on each slide, both hyperlinks to my image sources (to credit those CC-licensed image creators!) and links to original papers and other materials. However, I try to use a URL-shortening service whenever possible. Most commonly, I use &lt;a href=&quot;bit.ly&quot;&gt;bit.ly&lt;/a&gt; and customize the shortlinks to be readable. For example, I’ve made &lt;a href=&quot;bit.ly/AllHailTheAlgorithm&quot;&gt;bit.ly/AllHailTheAlgorithm&lt;/a&gt;, which links to a piece of journalism by Al Jazeera called All Hail the Algorithm. It’s a simple-enough link  people watching can type it out as they watch, and again, I always distribute slides via twitter before I give a talk. St Thomas also has &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.stthomas.edu/login&quot;&gt;a link shortener&lt;/a&gt; if you want professional links with a St Thomas theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, slide animations are &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephanieevergreen.com/how-i-feel-about-slide-animations/&quot;&gt;usually distracting&lt;/a&gt;, so it’s best not to use them. However, if used carefully, animations can be very effective. One convention I’ve become slightly known for is embedding screen-capture videos into my slides, so I can show how a piece of software works or a piece of code executes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/hps9r7JZQP8?t=930&quot;&gt;example 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uLcd6tRTUEY?t=314&quot;&gt;example 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/wn5larsRHro?t=718&quot;&gt;example 3&lt;/a&gt;). Crucially, while I’m showing a video, I never am hitting play on something with sound. Instead, it’s a silent video and I get to talk over it live during my presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-slide-shows&quot;&gt;Building slide shows&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of platforms for making decks of slides. The most common are probably PowerPoint, Keynote, and Google Slides. Personally, I use Keynote because it works the most seamlessly on a Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to work more reproducibly, there are options like Beamer (the way to make slides using LaTeX, a typesetting language for math) and variations on RMarkdown that knit to PDF or HTML slide shows. Personally, I don’t think those platforms give me as much control as I want, and are a lot of overhead to learn. I only use them if I need to include a lot of typeset math, or (sometimes) code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with code, I often use Keynote because it makes it easier to get things exactly the size I want. I do use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://reprex.tidyverse.org/articles/articles/rtf.html&quot;&gt;reprex venue RTF&lt;/a&gt; to get code highlighting to paste into Keynote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our new world of online education, I’ve found myself doing a lot of video-recorded presentations. I find full-screen presentations with just a voiceover to be pretty hard to stay attentive to, so I try to have a picture-in-picture of myself talking any time I do one of these recordings. At least on my computer, using the widescreen (16:9) format for my slides rather than standard (4:3) format allows me to get a nice picture-in-picture automatically when recording from Zoom, and easily when recording with a tool like &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsproject.com/&quot;&gt;OBS&lt;/a&gt; as well. I did a short &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/BtSeEeeVzk0&quot;&gt;behind-the-scenes video&lt;/a&gt; of how I record using Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;giving-the-presentation&quot;&gt;Giving the presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m given the opportunity to present from my own computer, I always use the Keynote file and take advantage of all the settings I can pre-select (I have my presenter view customized, I know what will happen to my videos when I click, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have to use someone else’s computer, I export my slides to PDF and use the static slides for my presentation. Sometimes I will “print each stage of builds” if I’ve designed some type of buildable slide (text appearing on a slide, for example). This will end up creating more pages for my PDF, but is nicer while I present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also always export to PDF to share slides with others, and for that usecase I do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; “print each stage of builds.” People coming to my twitter or website for a copy of my slides are mostly skimming for links and takeaways, they don’t need the entire build-up of the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/_inundata/status/748681351864283136&quot;&gt;fast-talking R mafia&lt;/a&gt;, the thing I am reminding myself the most often while I speak is “slow down” (unless I’m giving a lighting talk where I &lt;a href=&quot;https://resources.rstudio.com/rstudio-conf-2020/lightning-talk-dr-amelia-mcnamara&quot;&gt;whiz through 30 slides in 5 minutes&lt;/a&gt;). It’s good to build in some places to pause as you speak, to give your audience a chance to process. When you finish talking about a slide, that can be a good place to pause. Nicky Case uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/uc5rfTkLzlY?t=142&quot;&gt;water breaks to good effect&lt;/a&gt; for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ending-your-talk&quot;&gt;Ending your talk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a strongly-held opinion that the last words out of your mouth at the end of a talk should always be “thank you.” This makes it clear you are finished speaking, and also gives the audience a non-awkward opportunity to clap. If you say “any questions?” then the audience claps but it’s a little awkward (can you tell I have social anxiety?). Hadley Wickham says &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hadleywickham/status/1220867364557934593?s=20&quot;&gt;the key is to end with a firm statement (ie. no rising intonation) and then pause&lt;/a&gt;, but coming up with something to say in a firm way that is not “thank you” is usually beyond me at the end of a talk. Just like having a patter to begin a talk, having one to end your talk also helps free your brain up to think about other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last slide always says “thank you” in big letters, to remind me to say this. I also typically repeat the same image background as my original slide, and repeat how to contact me. Jenny Bryan and Mara Averick &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2018/07/carpe-talk/&quot;&gt;disagree with me a little on this point&lt;/a&gt;, and say it’s better to have a slide at the end with an overview and links. I think that’s probably great, but I often need the “thank you” cue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, that’s all I have to say about giving presentations. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2020/04/16/presentations.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2020/04/16/presentations.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/YouTubeTalks.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Deleting Facebook</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I recently took the plunge and deleted my Facebook account. This was a big decision for me, and I know other people are thinking about doing the same. So, I want to detail why I decided to delete my account, how I prepared to do it while also saving my data, and the way I’ve felt since I took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-did-it&quot;&gt;Why I did it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been thinking about deleting my Facebook account for several years, because I spend a fair amount of time teaching and speaking about data ethics and algorithmic inequality (e.g., my 2017 Otelia Cromwell Day workshop, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qRT3334Szis&quot;&gt;Algorithmic Accountability&lt;/a&gt;). If you are a Facebook user, you are probably at least vaguely aware the company doesn’t always do the right thing. I can’t cover everything they’ve done wrong, but here are a few things that come to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2013, Facebook was letting advertisers take your data (including your likes and profile picture) &lt;a href=&quot;https://mashable.com/2013/09/05/facebook-ads-photo/&quot;&gt;to include in ads to your friends&lt;/a&gt;. I became aware of this when I saw my dad’s photo in an ad. After this was exposed, Facebook gave users the opportunity to opt out of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2014, Facebook &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2014/06/28/facebook-manipulated-689003-users-emotions-for-science/#692ba3cd197c&quot;&gt;ran an experiment to manipulate emotions of users&lt;/a&gt;. This experiment was done without the oversight of an Institutional Review Board (the administrative body that protects human subjects in university studies). As someone commented on twitter, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/niftyc/status/482925976251154432&quot;&gt;“&lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; nobody was driven to suicide”&lt;/a&gt; by this experiment, but we don’t know.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facebook allowed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/19/technology/facebook-cambridge-analytica-explained.html&quot;&gt;Cambridge Analytica to get information on “more than 50 million Facebook users,”&lt;/a&gt; which may have helped them manipulate the 2016 election.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2016, it was shown that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/facebook-lets-advertisers-exclude-users-by-race&quot;&gt;Facebook was letting housing advertisers discriminate by race&lt;/a&gt;, in violation of federal law. Facebook said they would fix the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/facebook-advertising-discrimination-housing-race-sex-national-origin&quot;&gt;Facebook was still letting housing advertisers discriminate by race&lt;/a&gt;. Facebook said they would fix the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2018, it was shown that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/facebook-is-letting-job-advertisers-target-only-men&quot;&gt;Facebook was letting job advertisers target only men&lt;/a&gt;, in violation of federal law. Facebook said they would fix the issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As of March 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propublica.org/article/facebook-ads-discrimination-settlement-housing-employment-credit&quot;&gt;Facebook says “advertisers can no longer target users by age, gender and ZIP code for housing, employment and credit offers”&lt;/a&gt;, but it took years for this change to be made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Of course, Facebook is tracking you all over the web, not just while you’re on their site. And, it seems clear they maintain &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/4/11/17225482/facebook-shadow-profiles-zuckerberg-congress-data-privacy&quot;&gt;shadow profiles of people who don’t have accounts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The thing that pushed me over the edge was Facebook saying they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/facebook-political-ads-fact-check-policy-explained-2019-11&quot;&gt;wouldn’t fact-check political ads&lt;/a&gt;. In general, Facebook &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; fact-check ads, and uses a third-party fact checking service. But, they won’t apply the same policy to political ads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook is essentially an ad company, and they develop their platform to keep you hooked enough to serve you more ads. Although Mark Zuckerberg already has a net worth of ~$70 billion, he is still valuing making more money over doing the right thing. While most social networks operate on the same principles, other companies have left money on the table in order to do the right thing. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90396075/pinterest-is-escalating-its-fight-against-anti-vaxxers-as-measles-surge-in-the-u-s&quot;&gt;Pinterest now blocks anti-vaccination searches&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for my own personal sanity (less time looking at my phone!) as well as my principles (data companies should do good with data!) I decided to delete my account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I knew I was doing the right thing, it was still really hard. I was an extremely active Facebook user. From when I joined the site in 2006 until I deleted my account in 2019, I almost always had a Facebook tab open on my computer, and as soon as I had a smartphone I had the app on my phone. Looking back at RescueTime data, it appears I spent about 15 minutes a day on Facebook most days. I was actually surprised to see such a low number, because it felt like I was on Facebook all day. I would probably click on my Facebook tab at least once an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I was so attached to Facebook, I didn’t want to delete my account and lose all my data. So, instead of just hitting the button, I embarked on a journey to rescue the data I wanted to keep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-did-it&quot;&gt;How I did it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t do any sort of tapering to my use. I posted a warning to my Facebook two weeks before I deleted my account, saying I was leaving the platform and giving people the opportunity to subscribe to my newsletter. The text of what I posted is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/deleting_facebook/blob/master/LeavingFacebook.txt&quot;&gt;on my GitHub&lt;/a&gt; if you want to see what I wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout those two weeks I continued to use Facebook on both my computer and my phone. In fact, I might have been on Facebook even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; during that time, as I worked my way through my friend list, reaching out to people and getting other contact methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first move was to download all the data Facebook makes available to users through their Download Your Information tool. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/help/1701730696756992?helpref=hc_global_nav&quot;&gt;Facebook has instructions on how to do this&lt;/a&gt;. My main piece of advice is to think carefully about whether you want .html or .json files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTML is probably the most appropriate for most (non-programmer) people, because the HTML file structure makes it easy to browse through your data on your computer. The files kind of mimic the Facebook experience, so you can click on a file called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;your_photos.html&lt;/code&gt; and see a page with links to each of your Facebook photo albums. If you click through to an album, you will get a page with each photo and the associated comments on the picture. It’s a nice interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the HTML file structures are nasty. I didn’t see the JSON option, so I thought my only option was to use the HTML files. In order to parse out my friend list to a useful csv file, I had to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rvest&lt;/code&gt;. My code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/deleting_facebook/blob/master/FacebookFriends.md&quot;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; in case you find yourself in that same situation. But, to avoid this, I recommend getting at least some of your information in JSON format. Eventually, I downloaded all my data twice, once in each format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had the parsed csv file, I turned it into a Google Sheet. This is both a backup of my data and a centrally-accessible place to store it. (A side note– I have put my Facebook data all over the cloud. This might seem counter-intuitive, but I’m not worried about an individual hacker accessing my data, I wanted to remove myself from Facebook using my data in their ad machine.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of several days, I worked my way through my entire friend list (625 friends) and recorded some meta-data about them. I used Facebook as a sort of external brain for my social network. What is that person’s married name? Facebook knows. Which of the two people with the same first name did I go to college with, and which one is the partner of my colleague? Facebook knows. I knew that once I lost the ability to go to friends’ profiles to see their pictures and our list of mutual friends, I would lose a lot of my “memory” of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends’ pictures and mutual friends don’t come with your Facebook data download. I decided I didn’t need all that data (which I could have scraped) but that I would go through and categorize each person with a “rank,” a general way I knew them, and then any additional notes I would need in order to recall who they were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My rank variable was a value from 1 to 4, with 1 being my very best friends and close family, and 4 being people I probably should have unfriended because we had almost no connection. It felt a little scummy to rank people like that, but I know Facebook probably had an algorithmically-generated score in the background already, to determine whose posts I saw most often. I went through my friend list in reverse order of becoming Facebook friends, and it was such an interesting exercise. A sort of Marie Kondo of the network. (As a side note, I loved &lt;a href=&quot;https://tokimeki-unfollow.glitch.me/&quot;&gt;Tokimeki Unfollow&lt;/a&gt;, which is exactly that for your Twitter follows.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going through all my friends, here is the distribution of my friend rankings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/facebook_friends_rank.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Distribution of friend ranks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So interesting! It looks linear, and the numbers in each category seem to follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar%27s_number&quot;&gt;Dunbar’s number&lt;/a&gt;. I have 18 people I characterized as 1s (my support clique and sympathy group), 86 who are 2s (my active network), and 202 who are 3s (my personal network).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also interesting to see how I knew people,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/facebook_friends_how.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Distribution of how I know people&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was homeschooled as a child, so that covers the elementary and middle school years. Cincinnati was my first year of college, Macalester was where I transferred and finished my BA, UCLA was my PhD. I like the big categories of “friend of a friend” and “family of a friend.” I used &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;forcats::fct_lump&lt;/code&gt; to lump together small categories, because there were a lot of little categories that I’m less comfortable sharing with the wider internet! But again, cool insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had my friend list in an accessible place, and notes to myself about how I knew people, I felt pretty comfortable with my data. But, there were still two more big things I wanted from Facebook that didn’t come in their data download:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;friends’ birthdays&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tagged photos of me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook used to let users download their friends’ birthdays to a local calendar. However, they recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitaltrends.com/news/facebook-removes-friends-birthday-export/&quot;&gt;changed their policy&lt;/a&gt;, and that feature has been removed. I dug around online, and found a python scraper by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mobeigi&quot;&gt;Mo Beigi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mobeigi/fb2cal&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. As he warns, using this script made facebook temporarily suspend my account because of suspected security issues. However, this was a good reminder to change my Facebook password (something which happened repeatedly as I was working on scraping data). The script worked so well that I don’t have a clear memory of it anymore!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I ran the scraper, I had a .ics file with all 625 Facebook friends’ birthdays. However, I didn’t want to add all of them to my calendar, just my 104 close friends. So, I had to parse the .ics file and filter out just those birthdays. This process was tricky, mostly because I couldn’t make the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;calendar&lt;/code&gt; package work on the ics file I got from the scraper. Again, my code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/deleting_facebook/blob/master/parsing_birthdays.md&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, scroll down to get to the useful stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting insight from this process was that 21% of my close friends didn’t have their birthdays on Facebook. I’d guess this is in response to the feeling that Facebook is too invasive with their data collection. So now I have a list of people who I need to ask for their birthday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most challenging part of my data-rescue endeavor was rescuing my tagged photos. Again, I was a very active Facebook user with hundreds of friends. Over the 13 years I was on the site, I posted a lot of photos (1781, in fact). It was nice to get them in my Facebook data download. But, I would guess that I have almost all those files elsewhere, on my computer or my phone. The Facebook albums give me a curated selection of photos, and they’re batched into folders to make them easier to see. And of course, I also got the comments on my photos. But for the files themselves, not so useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Facebook does not give you in your data download are your tagged photos. It considers them to be your friends’ data, which I guess is fair. But, I wanted those photos! I had 878 tagged photos on Facebook, so going through them one by one and right-clicking to download didn’t make sense. I looked into scrapers online, and found several in python. However, I wasn’t able to get any of those scrapers to work. My suspicion is that Facebook changed their page structure to thwart those particular scrapers, and I’m not good enough at python to debug that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/deleting_facebook/blob/master/FacebookPhotosOfYou.md&quot;&gt;I wrote my own scraper in R&lt;/a&gt;. This scraper was very likely not the most efficient– it used &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RSelenium&lt;/code&gt; to drive a browser, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop to click through each picture because I couldn’t think of how to vectorize it, and the whole thing happened in real time (the browser was up and I got to watch it go through all the photos). In &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RSelenium&lt;/code&gt; I just grabbed the image urls, because I couldn’t figure out how to do the download right there, and I used another &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop and the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; library to download the images after the fact. However, this scraping code has the advantage of being (I think) very easy to read, so if Facebook changes their page structure I’d guess it will be possible to adjust the code to work again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had my 1781 uploaded photos and 878 tagged photos on my computer, I decided I wanted some of them physically printed. Somehow, when those photos were on Facebook they felt “safe” and like I would have access to them forever. But once they were on my computer, even though they were backed up, they felt insecure. Of those ~2500 photos, I chose ~500 I wanted printed, and uploaded them to Shutterfly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did my initial order before I deleted my Facebook account, and was able to use Shutterfly’s Facebook Connect feature to import some photos directly from my photo albums. However, tagged photos are again not available there, so I had to upload those manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got my order, I was pretty shocked to see what ~500 photos looks like in a stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/photo_stack.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Stack of 500 photos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine 2500 photos! I bought myself a photo album with those plastic sleeves, and have been working on getting the photos in there. I’ve got a few more to go, mostly because Shutterfly sent my prints in random order. I uploaded them chronologically, but that is not how the order arrives. Luckily, they do automatically print metadata on the back of their photos, so some of my prints came with Facebook captions, some came with dates, and some came with file names on the back. I haven’t spent enough time examining the pattern to be able to determine how those different pieces of metadata were chosen. But, they were all helpful when trying to remember when a photo was from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve gone, I’ve tried to label the backs of photos with names and dates. However, this has proven to be pretty difficult! If I got to go back and do this again, I’d print and organize the photos before I deleted my Facebook account, because it became difficult to remember some names. If I’d still had my profile, I could have looked at who was tagged in a photo, or used my “external brain” to make connections with people who weren’t tagged (“she’s friends with Katie, let’s go look at Katie and my mutual friends”). As it was, I ended up messaging people on other platforms to see if they could help me. Actually a pretty fun social activity, but it added to the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/album.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Photo album with 500 photos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise of printing and organizing 500 photos made me want to do a larger art project and physicalize all my Facebook data– print all 2500 photos, and make all my Facebook comments and Messenger messages into a book, a la &lt;a href=&quot;http://feltron.com/&quot;&gt;Nicholas Felton&lt;/a&gt;. Do you remember when he cataloged all communication for a year, and would print a book of all his communications with a particular person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is the one of communications with his girlfriend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;https://feltron.tumblr.com/post/95211354121/to-visualize-a-year-of-communication-required&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/felton_book.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nicholas Felton&#39;s book of communications&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was awed by the physicality of that data, but I’m sure my Facebook data would be even larger when printed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re getting a little out of order now, but one of the most important parts of the process is of course to delete you actual account! If you are leaving Facebook for the same reasons I was (abuse of data in support of ad revenue), you need to actually delete your account rather than deactivate it. If you deactivate your account, Facebook gets to &lt;a href=&quot;https://deletefacebook.com/deactivate/&quot;&gt;keep using&lt;/a&gt; your valuable data. (Of course, they might actually keep using it after you delete your account, but that would go against their Terms of Use.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/deleting_facebook/blob/master/LeavingFacebook.txt&quot;&gt;initial announcement&lt;/a&gt; that I was leaving Facebook on October 8. The following two weeks were a flurry of activity, much of it documented above (plus, my job and normal life stuff…). On October 22, I went through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.com/help/delete_account&quot;&gt;deletion process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing Facebook asks is if you really want to delete your account, or just deactivate it. The default is deactivate. I chose delete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/DeactivateDelete.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Do you want to deactivate or delete your account?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, you’re given a warning, with the option to keep Messenger and to download your information. I had already decided to delete Messenger and downloaded my information twice (once as html and once as json). But, this step might slow you down again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/DeleteWarning.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Permanently delete account&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to enter your password to confirm your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/EnterPassword.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Enter password&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final warning,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/ConfirmAgain.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Confirm again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you’re deleted! (Well, not really, because they give you 30 days to change your mind, and if you log in during that time you have to restart the whole process!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/DeletionEmail.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Deletion email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was somewhat surprised that this was the last email I got from Facebook. I was expecting a flurry of “are you sure??” emails as the date of permanent deletion approached. But perhaps they have studied user behavior and realized that if you get this far you aren’t going to change your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-way-i-feel&quot;&gt;The way I feel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been more than two months since I have logged in to Facebook (and a month since my account was actually deleted) and I have been shocked by how little I have missed Facebook. There have been a handful of times I’ve been somewhere and felt bored, anxious, or awkward, and have reached for my phone hoping to open Facebook. But, that’s about it. Unsurprisingly, I’ve been able to find other apps for that little twitch (something to work on in 2020!), so the lack of Facebook in particular hasn’t bothered me. I do know that I’m missing out on things. I miss being able to see regular posts of my friends’ kids (and, the kids of acquaintances who I probably can’t reach out to asking for photos!). I miss seeing what my far-flung family is up to. I know I’ve missed a couple event invites, and certainly the “events around town” feature that exposed me to things I wouldn’t have otherwise heard of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been interesting to see how my social connections have changed. I’ve transitioned one of my best friends to Signal for messaging, after years of using Messenger. Signal isn’t great for sharing photos, and we haven’t found a perfect solution. Right now we’re just sending emails with photo attachments. I’ve been getting more memes texted and emailed to me (several people have said, “I went to share it with you on Facebook and you weren’t there!”). Overall, it seems like my connections have gotten more personal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been talking to lots of people about my decision to delete my account, and a common refrain I hear from people is, “I could never delete &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; account because [x].” I know there are many great things about Facebook. It connects people with rare diseases across the globe, it gets used by parents to organize school-related events for children, and on and on. In particular, Facebook is a place for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/4/28/17293056/facebook-deletefacebook-social-network-monopoly&quot;&gt;emotional labor&lt;/a&gt;, so it can be particularly hard for women and mothers to leave it. As Vicki Boykis has pointed out, leaving Facebook is &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.vickiboykis.com/2019/04/25/digital-noise/&quot;&gt;a luxury&lt;/a&gt; that not everyone can afford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because I deleted my account doesn’t mean I’m judging you for not deleting yours. But, I would encourage you to think about whether you actually need it, or whether it just feels scary to go without. The more people who leave Facebook, the bigger a message we send that the platform can’t abuse our desire for social connection to sell more ads at any cost.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2019/12/29/Deleting-Facebook.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2019/12/29/Deleting-Facebook.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/photo_stack.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Key Attributes of a Modern Statistical Computing Tool</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/1191464296779255814?s=20&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; that the first paper to come out of my dissertation was published. I got my PhD in 2015, and it’s now 2019. That means I’ve been thinking about this work for more than four years (in fact, it’s probably closer to seven!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read the paper, it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2018.1482784&quot;&gt;now published&lt;/a&gt; in Volume 73, Issue 4 of The American Statistician. I was given 100 free e-prints, which are available until they run out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/eprint/WNRYZCHGUMCEUIEC9C9X/full?target=10.1080/00031305.2018.1482784&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. A pre-print of this paper is also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1610.00985&quot;&gt;the arXiv&lt;/a&gt; if you want a non-paywalled version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so delighted to finally have this thing I have been thinking about since 2012 finally off my mental list and into the real world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/KeyAttributes.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;The print version of this paper!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the story of how this paper came to be is written into &lt;a href=&quot;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/1mm9303x&quot;&gt;my dissertation&lt;/a&gt;, but I thought I would summarize it briefly here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, as a graduate student I had the opportunity to run some professional development (PD) for high school teachers to help them develop their R skills. The PD was about a week long, and it was for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.exploringcs.org/&quot;&gt;Exploring Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; (ECS) curriculum. Over the course of the week, I managed to prove myself to the PIs of the grant (particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https://gseis.ucla.edu/directory/jane-margolis/&quot;&gt;Jane Margolis&lt;/a&gt;) because of my ability to communicate with both technical folks and tech-phobic people. The ECS team immediately found some hours for me to continue work with them, and then I was quickly incorporated into the next grant the team developed– Mobilize. The Mobilize project had some big goals, including developing data science technology and curriculum for the high school level, running PD, research and evaluation of our products, changing educational policy at the national and state level, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the next three years, I ran hundreds of hours of professional development for teachers, mostly teaching them technical skills to support data science curriculum, but also some basic statistical concepts. This was extremely difficult task, because many teachers had never taken a statistics course (or if they had, it was years before), or programmed in any language. Over the course of the grant, we iterated on a number of tools. In order, we tried:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;base R, with the standard R GUI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deducer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;formula syntax R, through an RStudio server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of iterating through tools and attempting to teach them to novices gave me a lot of perspective on what makes a good tool for someone who is just starting out. Since then, I’ve taught R in many other contexts (in undergraduate college courses, at conference workshops for biostatisticians, data journalists, and generally for data practitioners).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel to my experience starting to teach R and other technical tools, as a graduate student I had the time and opportunity to read hundreds of papers. This allowed me to think deeply about concepts from human-computer interaction, user experience design, and programming language design, and how these concepts interact with ideas of statistical computing. If you look at the references of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2018.1482784&quot;&gt;my recent paper&lt;/a&gt;, I think it’s clear this paper came from a dissertation, because it has almost 100 references. The two most influential pieces to my dissertation (and this derived work) were&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amstat.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00031305.1965.10479711#.XdA6_pNKjBI&quot;&gt;The Technical Tools of Statistics&lt;/a&gt;, by John Tukey (1965)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iase-web.org/documents/intstatreview/97.Biehler.pdf&quot;&gt;Software for Learning and for Doing Statistics&lt;/a&gt;, by Rolf Biehler (1997)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these papers lay out idealized attributes of statistical tools, and by clearly articulating the way tools should work in the future, they were able to manifest that future. (As &lt;a href=&quot;http://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/kay_3972189.cfm&quot;&gt;Alan Kay&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://quoteinvestigator.com/2012/09/27/invent-the-future/&quot;&gt;says&lt;/a&gt;, “the best way to predict the future is to create it.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tukey’s case, his paper clearly influenced his own software work (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B7XoW2qiFUA&quot;&gt;prim9&lt;/a&gt;, a tool for visualizing high-dimensional data from the 1970s, which you interacted with using a light pen), as well as tools like S, S-Plus, and R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biehler’s paper laid the groundwork for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tinkerplots.com/&quot;&gt;TinkerPlots&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://fathom.concord.org/&quot;&gt;Fathom&lt;/a&gt;, two tools for teaching statistics that allowed learners to directly interact with their data and build intuition about statistics. Sadly, both TinkerPlots and Fathom are now mostly defunct, although The Concord Consortium is working on a next-generation tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://codap.concord.org/&quot;&gt;CODAP&lt;/a&gt;, the Common Online Data Analysis Platform (full disclosure, I have consulted with The Concord Consortium).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found these papers influential, and I saw an opportunity to reconsider the necessary components for statistical software again. Nearly 20 years had passed since Biehler’s paper, and advances in computer graphics and software in general have made more things possible. Working from the inspiration of Tukey and Biehler, and guided by my on-the-ground experience teaching R as well as my extensive literature review, I developed a list of ten attributes I think are necessary for a modern statistical computing tool. These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessibility&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy entry for novice users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data as a first-order persistent object&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for a cycle of exploratory and confirmatory analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexible plot creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for randomization throughout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interactivity at every level&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inherent documentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple support for narrative, publishing, and reproducibility&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexibility to build extensions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a tl;dr, I’ll summarize those for you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessibility: The tool should be accessible to lots of people. It needs to work on all major operating systems, be free or cheap, and be accessible to people with disabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy entry for novice users: The tool should be easy to get started using, with little or no guidance. The “threshold” to success should be low.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data as a first-order persistent object: Data should be the foundational object for a statistical tool. When you work with data, it should always be as a copy (looking at you, Excel).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for a cycle of exploratory and confirmatory analysis: It should be easy to iterate through the “data cycle” in the tool.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexible plot creation: Statistical tools should allow you to create new visualization types, following the Grammar of Graphics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for randomization throughout: As a pedagogical tool and a more flexible method for inference, it is important a tool support simulation methods like randomization and the bootstrap, both for numerical statistics and for graphics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interactivity at every level: An analyst should find it easy to adjust parameters as they work and see the effects of parameters early in their analysis on later pieces of the analysis. Published results should be interactive to allow readers to do the same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inherent documentation: The tool should tell (or show) you what it is going to do. Textual languages should aim for function names that are as human-readable as possible, and graphical user interfaces should strive to visualize what is happening in each step.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple support for narrative, publishing, and reproducibility: Whatever you do in your tool should be easily documented, whether as a static document with textual code or a list of operations in a GUI. Narrative and analysis should be encouraged to mix in literate documents.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexibility to build extensions: The complement to 2), the tool needs a high ceiling, so you don’t “experience out” of the tool. It should be possible to implement new functions and extend functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these attributes encompass a lot of what is important for a tool. Over the years I’ve been thinking about this, I’ve refined the attributes and tried to make them as comprehensive as possible. But, I’m sure there are pieces that are missing. For example, it has been pointed out that I don’t talk about the correctness of the implementations. To me, that goes without saying– if it’s a tool for statistical computing, it needs to do statistics properly! But of course, we have seen that isn’t always a safe assumption. I explicitly didn’t touch things like computing speed, because I was considering this from a human usability perspective. If you have a good, usable tool, and it allows you to build extensions, someone will fix the speed issue. Much harder to fix are things like inherent documentation, which we have seen Hadley Wickham working through with things like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pivot_longer()&lt;/code&gt;, the next generation of what was formerly  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gather()&lt;/code&gt;, formerly &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cast()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal with writing this paper was to give practitioners and educators a framework for evaluating a tool, and to inspire people who build tools themselves. I hadn’t seen anything like this since 1997, so I decided it was time to re-open the conversation. But, I do want it to be a conversation. What else should we be aiming for as we design the next iteration of statistical computing tools?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/papers/2019/11/26/Key-Attributes.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/papers/2019/11/26/Key-Attributes.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/KeyAttributes.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A tidy dress</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;That’s right ya’ll, I made myself a R hex logo dress!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/HexDress.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;The hex dress&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about this dress for at least a year, if not longer. But I finally had a summer where I wasn’t moving, and I decided to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step was looking for a good nested hex image. I searched the internet, and came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mitchelloharawild.com/blog/hexwall/&quot;&gt;a way to use magick&lt;/a&gt; to nest hexes. I love R and reproducible work, so I played around with this code for a while to see if it would do what I wanted. Pretty quickly, I ran into problems with non-standard hex sizes, as well as errors I struggled to debug. So, I turned away from code. 😭&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may or may not know that I started college at art/design school. While I realized design wasn’t for me, I have a year of color theory, art history, 3D design, digital design, etc., under my belt. This means I can kinda-sorta use Adobe Illustrator. I’m maintaining a version of CS6 on my computer to avoid paying for Creative Suite (sorry if that means my files are deprecated!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gathered the RStudio hexes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rstudio/hex-stickers/&quot;&gt;their GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;, and  searched the internet to find a few additional hexes. My final design uses hex logos from blogdown, bookdown, broom, devtools, dplyr, feather, forcats, fs, ggplot2, glue, googlesheets, haven, hms, janeaustenr, knitr, lobstr, lubridate, magrittr, packrat, parsnip, plumber, readr, readxl, reprex, rladies, rlang, rmarkdown, roxygen2, rstudio, scales, shiny, skimr, stringr, testthat, tibble, tidyverse, usethis, visdat, withr, xaringan, and yardstick. Mostly, I picked packages that I personally use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most time-consuming part of this entire process was laying out the hexes. As I learned, not all hexes are exactly the same size. Some aren’t quite hexagons. And, when you’re going to make fabric, you need the right edge of the design to match up perfectly with the left edge, and the top with the bottom. There was lots of zooming in, fiddling with dimensions, and nudging objects by a pixel one direction or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, I was in the midst of this nudging while I was at the Columbia, MD &lt;a href=&quot;https://ecstatic-mclean-a0b3e0.netlify.com/blog/schedule-howard/&quot;&gt;StatPREP workshop&lt;/a&gt;. I ran my idea past &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macalester.edu/~kaplan/&quot;&gt;Danny Kaplan&lt;/a&gt;. He looked at my design and immediately could see it was too busy. I was nesting all these extremely colorful, highly saturated images right next to each other, and it was overwhelming. His initial suggestion was to leave blank spaces in between the hexes, but I really wanted tiles. So then he suggested making many of the hexes less opaque, with just a few at full opacity. This turned out to be genius, because the lighter areas were easier to match together when sewing, and hid some of the issues with the edge matching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I tried using R to generate random 0s and 1s to tell me which to make full opacity. This ended up looking terrible (true randomness doesn’t look random to humans!), so I ended up hand-choosing the opaque hexes. My goal was to emulate the way hexes often look on laptop lids (here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://devlids.com/lids/ameliamn&quot;&gt;my laptop&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://devlids.com/&quot;&gt;devlids&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Laptop stickers spotted in the wild at the Southern MN Stat Chat! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/3RipGl3tI7&quot;&gt;https://t.co/3RipGl3tI7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/KJVYGr6Vi7&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/KJVYGr6Vi7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/1121915555177480192?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 26, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had the Illustrator file, I exported to JPG. I’ve written about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2014/12/12/FabricPosters.html&quot;&gt;making fabric posters on Spoonflower&lt;/a&gt;, so I knew about their upload process. You need to upload a TIF, JPG, PNG, or GIF. Can’t say why I chose JPG on this particular occasion. The important thing is to make sure your DPI (dots per inch) is high enough to look good. Spoonflower recommends 150 DPI, but I think I used 300 DPI. More on this later. The Illustrator file and exported JPG are both on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ameliamn/hexfabric&quot;&gt;hexfabric GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to adjust the design, include different hexes, etc., feel free to use and modify those files!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I am mostly a procrastinator, I actually took my time on this project. So, once I had uploaded the design I got a “test swatch” printed from Spoonflower. I’m so glad I did, because I didn’t realize how big the hexes initially were! I think this was a result of the DPI, perhaps if I had used the recommended 150 DPI the hexes would have come out how I expected. No problem, I used the “smaller” button on Spoonflower and got the design the way I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/large_hex_fabric.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Too-big hexes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another shocking bout of preparation, I decided to make a test dress out of a plain fabric before jumping in with the custom fabric. I chose not to use a pattern, but instead pattern off existing garments. I learned how to pattern from existing garments at a sewing makerspace in Northampton, MA while I lived there. Sadly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beehivesewing.com/&quot;&gt;the makerspace&lt;/a&gt; is now defunct, but the owner does have a neat &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/shop/BeehiveSewingStudios&quot;&gt;etsy shop&lt;/a&gt;! (Fun fact– I got a too-big conference tshirt from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openvisconf.com/2017/&quot;&gt;OpenVisConf&lt;/a&gt; a few years ago, and I used the material from that shirt to re-make a shirt that fit as my class project, patterning off a Shiny tshirt.) If you’re a loyal reader of this blog, you may remember that I get &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2014/06/12/Sweater_Variation.html&quot;&gt;too attached to particular items of clothing&lt;/a&gt;, so patterning off existing garments lets me give old things new life. I modified my tshirt pattern from the makerspace class for the bodice, and patterned the skirt off an Old Navy dress I loved but had worn out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the challenge with drafting your own pattern is that you don’t get a nice set of instructions! Luckily, I had my t-shirt instruction booklet from the makerspace class, and a salesperson at my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.treadleyardgoods.com/&quot;&gt;local fabric shop&lt;/a&gt; had told me about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colettepatterns.com/catalog/moneta&quot;&gt;a pattern&lt;/a&gt; that sounded similar to what I was sewing, and suggested looking for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/gshREJvdCCM?t=438&quot;&gt;sew-along tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to explain how to do the clear elastic gathering for the skirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two yards of grey jersey material, so I cut out all the pieces out of that to verify that two yards was a reasonable amount of fabric. For plain material, I think I could have gotten the dress cut from one yard of material, but I knew that with a patterned material I’d need more wiggle room. Satisfied that two yards was enough, I threw caution to the wind and purchased two yards of my new design from Spoonflower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interim, I sewed up the grey practice dress. When working with stretchy material (like jersey), it’s best to use a Serger rather than a regular sewing machine. Sergers do “interlock” stitching, which holds together better on stretchy material. Luckily for me, my mom has a Serger, and she was willing to let me use it. Over a couple sewing sessions at her house, the dress came together. I was really glad I chose to do the practice dress, because I made all sorts of mistakes and discovered issues in my pattern. And, most importantly, while I was sewing at her house my mom mentioned POCKETS! My original Old Navy dress didn’t have pockets, so I hadn’t patterned them. But of course the internet &lt;a href=&quot;http://seaminglysmitten.blogspot.com/2014/10/tutorial-how-to-sew-knit-dress-with.html&quot;&gt;knows how to make pockets&lt;/a&gt;. Those got added in as I went. With the grey dress done, I was ready when my custom fabric arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/small_hex_fabric.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Smaller hex fabric&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you want to wash and dry fabric before you work with it, to avoid issues with shrinkage. I washed and dried my fabric and was on to the second-hardest part of the project: cutting out the pieces for the final dress. I wanted everything to be straight, upright, and ideally match up along seams. So hard! The other tricky thing was the neckband, which I knew would look busy if I cut it out of the patterned fabric. I thought of trying to buy some plain white jersey for the neckband, but the store I looked at didn’t have anything that matched the fabric weight. But, when my Spoonflower order arrived, I realized there was a little white edge outside the print area that I could use! Very fortuitous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sewing went much quicker on the tidyverse dress than the grey one, because I had worked out all the kinks ahead of time. I did my best to match up the pattern wherever possible, but because of the gathering in the skirt and the curved seams on the shoulders, it didn’t often happen. However, those low-opacity hexes proved to be very forgiving for overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I had access to a Serger for doing most of the work, I needed a different machine to finish the hems. Apart from the community and the classes, the thing I miss most about the sewing makerspace I used to go to is the coverhem machine. If you look at the hem of almost any commercially-made garment you have (especially if it’s knit), it probably was done on a coverhem. The back looks like Serger stitches, all interlocked, and the front has two rows of parallel stitches that look like they were done on a regular machine. As far as I can tell, there’s nowhere in Minneapolis to use a coverhem machine, so I had to learn to do knit hems on a regular sewing machine. I’ve been following &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/crazyauntpurl/&quot;&gt;crazyauntpurl&lt;/a&gt; since she had a blogspot blog, and she sews with knits on her standard machine, so I knew it was possible. Again, my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.treadleyardgoods.com/&quot;&gt;local fabric shop&lt;/a&gt; employee helped me find a good &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Schmetz-Stretch-Twin-Needles-Size/dp/B002F01F7U?sa-no-redirect=1&amp;amp;pldnSite=1&quot;&gt;twin needle&lt;/a&gt; I could use on my machine, and reminded me to make sure my needle position was centered and my machine was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on zig-zag. The hems turned out pretty well, although they “tunneled” a little, so if I was going to do this again I would find some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mariadenmark.com/2014/08/twin-needle-hem/&quot;&gt;interfacing to stabilize the seams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/1162030771466645506&quot;&gt;best friend&lt;/a&gt; came over for the very end of the sewing process to do some documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/sewing.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Sewing the hems of my dress&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the dress was finished, I put it on and she did an awesome photoshoot of me in front of all the photogenic walls in my neighborhood!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/HexDress2.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;The hex dress in front of a different wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dress made its debut at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rnorthconference.github.io/&quot;&gt;2019 noRth conference&lt;/a&gt;, where it was a definite hit. I’m excited to see how much it sticks out in group photos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, people on twitter immediately wanted their own version. If you’ve read this far into my post, I hope you can understand why I’m not getting into the custom-dressmaking business! I am definitely an amateur when it comes to sewing. As I said on Twitter,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;If you want to edit the design, I’ve put the files on GitHub, &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/47FC2uMMCn&quot;&gt;https://t.co/47FC2uMMCn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#rstats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/tidyverse?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/1162359528178036737?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not everyone has the skills to sew their own projects! So, I started looking into some of the online retailers suggested by folks on Twitter. I haven’t seen any of these products yet, so I can’t really vouch for their quality, but if you want to make the leap here are a couple places you can buy things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spoonflower.com/en/home-decor/dining/rectangular-table-cloth/8922748-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes-by-ameliamn&quot;&gt;Table cloth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://roostery.com/p/frizzle-cloth-cocktail-napkins/8922748-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes-by-ameliamn&quot;&gt;cocktail napkins&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://roostery.com/p/orpington-linen-tea-towels/8922748-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes-by-ameliamn&quot;&gt;tea towels&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spoonflower.com/en/home-decor/bedding/duvet-cover/8922748-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes-by-ameliamn&quot;&gt;duvet cover&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://roostery.com/p/catalan-square-throw-pillow/8922748-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes-by-ameliamn&quot;&gt;throw pillow&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spoonflower.com/en/products/8922748-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes-by-ameliamn&quot;&gt;more housewares&lt;/a&gt; (scroll down) available on Spoonflower via Roostery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bigger hex version is coming to Spoonflower soon! I think that version looks better on the duvet cover and other large housewares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622264-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes?asc=u&amp;amp;p=a-line-dress&quot;&gt;A-line dress&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622264-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes?p=pencil-skirt&amp;amp;ref=available_products&quot;&gt;miniskirt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622264-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes?p=laptop-sleeve&amp;amp;ref=available_products&quot;&gt;laptop sleeve&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622264-r-hex-fabric-small-hexes&quot;&gt;many more items&lt;/a&gt; (scroll down and click “Also available on”) on Redbubble.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar products on Redbubble using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622162-r-hex-design-large-hexes&quot;&gt;large hexes&lt;/a&gt;, including a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622162-r-hex-design-large-hexes&quot;&gt;shower curtain&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622162-r-hex-design-large-hexes?p=blanket&amp;amp;ref=available_products&quot;&gt;throw blanket&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.redbubble.com/people/ameliamn/works/40622162-r-hex-design-large-hexes?p=tote-bag&amp;amp;ref=similar_products&quot;&gt;tote bag&lt;/a&gt;. Again, scroll down and click “Also available on” to see all options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zazzle.com/r_hex_mouse_pad-144405333200562879&quot;&gt;Regular mousepad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zazzle.com/r_hex_gel_mouse_pad-159993639402971234&quot;&gt;gel mousepad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zazzle.com/r_hex_baby_burp_cloth-256223453753317443&quot;&gt;baby burp cloth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zazzle.com/r_hex_bandana-256345773298354764&quot;&gt;bandana&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zazzle.com/store/ameliamn/products&quot;&gt;and more&lt;/a&gt; on Zazzle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Of course, the things most people want are really hard to find quality vendors for. I’ve heard requests for tshirts (working on it!), dresses with pockets (this may be impossible), leggings (working on it! Although this may be a weird design for leggings…), and pants (this seems impossible, too).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As above, if &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; find a site where you can upload a design, feel free to use the files &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ameliamn/hexfabric&quot;&gt;from GitHub&lt;/a&gt; to make your own products!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so excited to finally have this physical artifact I’ve been dreaming about, and I would love to see ya’ll get the same kind of joy!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2019/08/17/Tidy-Dress.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/misc/2019/08/17/Tidy-Dress.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/HexDress.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Wikipedia in the classroom: Gender, argh</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amelia.mn/sds236/index.html&quot;&gt;data journalism course&lt;/a&gt; I’m teaching this semester is a new offering for me. I may write up more of my reflections later, but for now I wanted to get some thoughts down about the experience of using Wikipedia as a pedagogical tool. At this point, I feel like it was too real-world of an experience for the class, and I inadvertently exposed my students to some gendered bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For their first writing assignment in the class (I am nothing if not ambitious!) I had the students author Wikipedia articles for people who did not have them. You can look at my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amelia.mn/sds236/Wikipedia.html&quot;&gt;assignment guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, but essentially I wanted them to research and write an article, but I gave credit for completion, rather than quality (particularly by Wikipedia’s metric). I generated a list of folks I thought were notable enough for articles, but told students they could choose someone else if they had an idea they wanted to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that not everyone I thought was notable actually had enough material on the web to meet the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Notability&quot;&gt;Wikipedia notability standards&lt;/a&gt;. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Charlotte_Wickham&quot;&gt;Charlotte Wickham&lt;/a&gt; might fall in that category. She seems notable to me, but there’s only a limited amount of press on her. I also learned a little too late that journalists often do not count as notable, because &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Notability_(journalists)&quot;&gt;Wikipedia has not accepted a specific notability standard for them&lt;/a&gt;. So, people like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Sisi_Wei&quot;&gt;Sisi Wei&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Ryann_Jones&quot;&gt;Ryann Jones&lt;/a&gt; might fail to meet the standard, even though there is quite a bit of material on the web about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 20 or so articles my students undertook, seven of them are now live on Wikipedia. I’ll admit to being a little confused about how articles end up in the main namespace– some things that I’ve written have just ended up there right away, while others get stuck with an “awaiting review” flag, and others are just in the draft namespace with no such tag. Oliver Keyes and Mikhail Popov offered me some guidance on the Friendly Tech Space Slack (it lives up to its name!) and the most recent conclusion is that I conincidentally had students do this assignment during an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Autoconfirmed_article_creation_trial/Post-trial_Research_Report&quot;&gt;Autoconfirmed article creation trial&lt;/a&gt; at Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those seven articles are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynn_Cherny&quot;&gt;Lynn Cherny&lt;/a&gt; (saved from deletion from a friendly editor with a female-sounding username)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janaya_Khan&quot;&gt;Janaya Khan&lt;/a&gt; (probably the best article to come out of this class, and one of the names the students came up with themselves!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffrey_T._Leek&quot;&gt;Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgia_Lupi&quot;&gt;Giorgia Lupi&lt;/a&gt; (may not actually have been reviewed yet, perhaps I just dropped it into the main namespace?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefanie_Posavec&quot;&gt;Stefanie Posavec&lt;/a&gt; (also may not have been reviewed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria_Stodden&quot;&gt;Victoria Stodden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jer_Thorp&quot;&gt;Jer Thorp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think those articles are fantastic, and I’m glad to see them added to Wikipedia! But, that means the vast majority of the articles my students wrote are either waiting for review, or have been rejected. The queue of articles waiting for review is long, and the flag says they are “reviewed in no specific order” but that it may take 8 weeks or more to get a review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have enough data here to back this up, but it seems that of the articles my students wrote that have already been reviewed, the ones about men (Jeff Leek and Jer Thorp) were reviewed quickly, given the benefit of the doubt (see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jeffrey_T._Leek&amp;amp;diff=828628510&amp;amp;oldid=824547453&quot;&gt;charitable comments on the article about Jeff Leek&lt;/a&gt;, even though the draft might not have been of the highest quality), and accepted. The ones about women are either still waiting to be reviewed, or have been rejected on grounds that I think are pretty weak (see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Amanda_Cox&quot;&gt;comment on the article about Amanda Cox&lt;/a&gt; that rejects her article because it says she served on the Federal Reserve Board, rather than that she worked at the Fed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the rejections that are getting me particularly riled up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Jennifer_(Jenny)_Bryan&quot;&gt;Jenny Bryan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Amanda_Cox&quot;&gt;Amanda Cox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Kim_Rees&quot;&gt;Kim Rees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Julia_Silge&quot;&gt;Julia Silge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Edit, May 2019: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jenny_Bryan&quot;&gt;Jenny&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amanda_Cox&quot;&gt;Amanda&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Rees&quot;&gt;Kim&lt;/a&gt; all have Wikipedia pages! Thanks to Jessamyn West for using her Wikipedia status to get &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mxfh/status/1047895894123794432&quot;&gt;Amanda&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/1051890145199345664&quot;&gt;Jenny&lt;/a&gt;’s articles pushed through.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think those people (women) are extremely notable, and we should work to get their pages up to snuff. Will you help me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another place you could jump in is trying to improve the articles we have that are still in the review queue (or that I’ve re-submitted after rejection), to hopefully forestall any issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Kennedy_Elliott&quot;&gt;Kennedy Elliot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Meredith_Broussard&quot;&gt;Meredith Broussard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Beatrice_Fischel-Bock&quot;&gt;Beatrice Fischel-Bock&lt;/a&gt; (another student-generated idea!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Lena_Groeger&quot;&gt;Lena Groeger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Mark_Hansen&quot;&gt;Mark Hansen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Sisi_Wei&quot;&gt;Sisi Wei&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draft:Charlotte_Wickham&quot;&gt;Charlotte Wickham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Edit, May 2019: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meredith_Broussard&quot;&gt;Meredith&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lena_Groeger&quot;&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Henry_Hansen&quot;&gt;Mark&lt;/a&gt; now have wikipedia pages!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if you’re looking for folks to write articles about, I’m giving away ideas for free! How about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mara Averick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nadieh Bremer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karl Broman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jen Christiansen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jessica Hullman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michelle Minkoff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hilary Parker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roger Peng&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olga Pierce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Robinson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irene Ros&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kara Woo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nathan Yau&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/03/20/Wikipedia-in-the-classroom.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/03/20/Wikipedia-in-the-classroom.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/Jenny_wikipedia.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Dagstuhl reflections</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last 10 days, I had the pleasure of attending &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rstudio.com/conference/&quot;&gt;rstudio::conf&lt;/a&gt; and the Dagstuhl seminar on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dagstuhl.de/en/program/calendar/semhp/?semnr=18061&quot;&gt;Evidence about Programmers for Programming Language Design&lt;/a&gt;. At rstudio::conf, I taught a two-day workshop on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/IntroToR&quot;&gt;Intro to R &amp;amp; RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, and at the Dagstuhl I mostly thought about exposing novices to programming in scientific contexts. So, there was a lot of overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://www.dagstuhl.de/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/Dagstuhl.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Schloss Dagstuhl&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dagstuhl.de/&quot;&gt;Schloss Dagstuhl&lt;/a&gt; is a historic castle that hosts workshops on topics related to computer science. The idea is to bring a small group of people (ours was about 35) together for a week to discuss a specific topic, with the goal of advancing the discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, what we wanted to advance was evidence about programmers for programming language design. Most programming languages are designed by intuition. But, given that the people who write programming languages are not always the people who use them, and we may be quite different from most users, this is likely not the best strategy. To improve, we’d like to put the “science” in “computer science.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began the week with presentations from a subset of the attendees (I wrote a separate post about my talk, &lt;a href=&quot;www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html&quot;&gt;Scientists Programming&lt;/a&gt;). The talks were aimed to ground us in the disparate disciplines we came from, including programming language design, eye tracking, science, and education. Then, we spent the remainder of the time in discussion, both small-group and full-group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was invited to the workshop by &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.cs.unlv.edu/stefika/&quot;&gt;Andreas Stefik&lt;/a&gt;, the absolute master of Skype networking with other academics. Stefik is known for developing an evidence-based programming language, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://quorumlanguage.com/&quot;&gt;Quorum&lt;/a&gt;. He was the only person I had interacted with at all before the conference, and our interactions had been limited to Skype and email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I discovered many connections with other folks once I was there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brad-meyers---better-language-goals&quot;&gt;Brad Meyers - better language goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first presentations of the workshop was by Brad Myers, who &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.BradA.Myers1.Slides1.pdf&quot;&gt;spoke about&lt;/a&gt; types of studies. However, what stuck out the most to me was his modified version of programming language goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Brad Myers started his &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/dagstuhl?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#dagstuhl&lt;/a&gt; talk by comparing programming language design goals:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(traditional)&lt;br /&gt;1. Correctness&lt;br /&gt;2. Performance (of code)&lt;br /&gt;3. Expressiveness&lt;br /&gt;4. Speed of compiling &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(usability)&lt;br /&gt;5. Understandability &lt;br /&gt;6. Ease of reading&lt;br /&gt;7. Modifiability&lt;br /&gt;8. Learnability&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/960502906821767168?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These goals reminded me of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1610.00985&quot;&gt;key attributes for a modern statistical programming tool&lt;/a&gt; paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neil-brown---data-on-student-errors&quot;&gt;Neil Brown - data on student errors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Brown, who worked on Greenfoot and BlueJ (IDEs for novices learning Java) was there. He and I talked about a principle I have absorbed from Greenfoot, that novices should never be presented with a blank screen, but instead some scaffolding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown has data on many students’ Java code from Blackbox, a way to capture data from students using BlueJ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Next up, Neil Brown of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KingsCollegeLon?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@KingsCollegeLon&lt;/a&gt; on analyzing programming data. BlueJay is an IDE for Java beginners, Blackbox can capture data about it. They have data on 300 million compilations, which is &lt;br /&gt;~3TB (compressed) of source code.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961530821596401664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teachers think they are good at predicting errors, but they actually are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Teachers are pretty certain they can predict what errors students will make. But, is that actually true?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961533231077175296?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This and many other great insights are in &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.NeilC.C.Brown1.Slides.pdf&quot;&gt;Brown’s slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brett-becker---better-errors&quot;&gt;Brett Becker - better errors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of errors, Brett Becker &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.BrettA.Becker2.Slides.pdf&quot;&gt;talked about&lt;/a&gt; improving compiler errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Becker: Error messages are accusatory and negative. Do we need to say “terminated” and “illegal”? “I’m going to get killed, and I’m going to jail.”&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961546402986897410?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;felienne---what-is-programming&quot;&gt;Felienne - what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; programming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to meet &lt;a href=&quot;http://felienne.com/&quot;&gt;Felienne&lt;/a&gt; in person after hearing Jenny Bryan &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jennybc/2016-06_spreadsheets&quot;&gt;talk about her&lt;/a&gt;, and following her on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/felienne&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; for years. Felienne gave my favorite &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.FelienneHermans1.Slides.key&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; of the workshop, which ranged from her work on spreadsheets as programming to her more recent work teaching students about “code smells” in Scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felienne asked “What is programming anyway?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;What is programming anyway? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; talking about 🧠head vs. ❤️. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/9qCfMq80KW&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9qCfMq80KW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961151780657729537?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She pointed out that while “every programmer ever” says that “Everyone should learn programming,” the community can be quite restrictive about what it considers to be “real programming.” Funnily enough, while everyone seemed to understand what she was saying, I also got pushback about &lt;a href=&quot;www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html&quot;&gt;my talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, we put users in one category and programmers in the other. But, there are many people who are “swimming in the water” of programming, and don’t even know they’re doing it. People who work deeply with spreadsheets are programmers, but they wouldn’t describe themselves that way. Again, this had reverberations with the &lt;a href=&quot;www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html&quot;&gt;scientists programming&lt;/a&gt; stuff I talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;After spreadsheets, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; started working on “code smells” in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scratch?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@scratch&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Ci9hGnesSh&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Ci9hGnesSh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961153216971931648?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felienne asked us two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Two dimensions: what is programming for? What is programming like? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; making a case for creativity and self-expression. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/GzzSRg5Rc0&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/GzzSRg5Rc0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961156021279444992?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One answer to “what is programming like?” is writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;One metaphor &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Felienne?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Felienne&lt;/a&gt; likes is programming as writing. There are many things that “count” as writing. Can be for yourself, can be for others, can be creative. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/eMlZhaJQ2D&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/eMlZhaJQ2D&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961159455948886016?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used it a lot, so I think programming as writing is a pretty robust metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baker-franke---teachability-and-learnability&quot;&gt;Baker Franke - teachability and learnability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another person I was delighted to meet was &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke&quot;&gt;Baker Franke&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.org/&quot;&gt;code.org&lt;/a&gt;, who it turns out worked on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://exploringcs.org/&quot;&gt;Exploring Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; (ECS) project before I joined it as a graduate student. At some point, I used the phrase “data the students can see themselves in” and he mentioned he’d written something about that in the early ECS curriculum. I’m now certain that’s where this idea (which I have fully integrated into my worldview) came from. It’s always fun to pin down those influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franke’s talk was also great, and teased out the subtle differences between learnability and teachability of a language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;We’ve been expanding our definition of language properties at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/dagstuhl?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#dagstuhl&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bakerfranke&lt;/a&gt; adding “teachability,” although he says this might not be a problem for language designers but a problem of pedagogy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/b1HlrgUJyH&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/b1HlrgUJyH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961185848539713538?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He echoed my feeling that consistency in teaching is so important (the reason why I teach only one R syntax in my intro classes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;For learners, consistency is good. Flexibility may not be helpful. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bakerfranke&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/g8NokrqC15&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/g8NokrqC15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961187475308863490?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has an idea about scaffolding in language design,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Mitch Resnik wanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scratch?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@scratch&lt;/a&gt; to have a low floor, high ceiling, wise walls. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bakerfranke?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bakerfranke&lt;/a&gt; wants a low floor, high ceiling, narrow walls to start, and wider walls as you get closer to the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961192913714675713?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was just a selection of the talks that related most directly to my interests. If you want to see the rest of them, they are posted on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/index.php?semnr=18061&quot;&gt;seminar materials page&lt;/a&gt;, and for more context on the people who attended (not all of whom presented), you can read &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.SWM.Slides.pdf&quot;&gt;everyone’s introductory slide&lt;/a&gt;, and check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/lists/evidenceaboutprogrammers&quot;&gt;twitter list&lt;/a&gt; I made of all the participants who are on twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-than-talks&quot;&gt;More than talks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, of course the point of the Dagstuhl was not just talks. It was making connections with other researchers. At every meal, we were assigned random seats to help us meet more people. We had structured time to think about programming language design studies we would like to see (thanks, Baker!) and time to discuss in groups. At the end of the last day, we developed a massive spreadsheet of current projects, future projects, and resources. I can see at least five potential projects I might lead or become involved with. The types of things I think about in terms of teaching statistics and R seemed to fit right in with the questions others at the workshop were asking– a novel feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I’m not the only one who feels this way. Several other folks have already written up their thoughts on the seminar, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/bits-and-behavior/designing-learnable-teachable-and-productive-programming-languages-dagstuhl-trip-report-81e41bde84bd&quot;&gt;Andy Ko&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cszero.wordpress.com/2018/02/11/dagstuhl-seminar-18061-evidence-about-programmers-for-programming-language-design/&quot;&gt;Brett Becker&lt;/a&gt;, and of course &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.felienne.com/archives/tag/dagstuhl&quot;&gt;Felienne’s liveblogging&lt;/a&gt;. 
Johannes Hofmeister captured his ideas on video,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-partner=&quot;tweetdeck&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Me, trying to capture all my ideas from the Dagstuhl seminar. Not a time lapse, actual speed of thoughts :D &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/kDolr7e8gb&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/kDolr7e8gb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Johannes Hofmeister (@pro_cessor) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pro_cessor/status/962765672110592000?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t wait to see where things go from here.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 05:43:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Dagstuhl-reflections.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Dagstuhl-reflections.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/Dagstuhl.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>More guys</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One incidental piece of the Dagstuhl is I thought more about the use of the term “guys.” While we were going around and doing our initial 3-minute introductions, I heard a lot of uses of “guys” that rubbed me the wrong way, so when I introduced myself I asked people to think about their gendered word choices throughout the seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regret doing this, because I think it marked me as someone who cares mainly about gender issues (I was there for the PL design stuff!) and I don’t think anyone really understood my point. People did become more aware of when they were saying it (and we used “squirrels!” as an interjection when someone did it), but not in a way that fostered inclusiveness. I’ll try to outline my personal opinion on the term here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/27/guys-guys-guys/&quot;&gt;the results&lt;/a&gt; from the survey I linked in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2017/12/19/On-Microaggressions.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I find it gender-neutral when people use the second person phrasing of “you guys.” This means it’s okay to address a mixed-gender group by saying “hey guys, what’s up?” “okay guys, let’s focus” “it’s time for us to go to lunch, guys,” etc. (That being said, I would encourage you to work toward saying something more inclusive, like “folks”, “peeps”, “ya’ll”, “everyone”, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem comes when you talk about people in the third person. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/27/guys-guys-guys/&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt;, phrases like “we’re going to need to hire a Python guy” or “I met a great Erlang guy” were perceived by the majority &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be gender-neutral. This is the useage that people were abusing in the Dagstuhl. I often heard people say, “I was talking to the google guys,” “I know the guys who worked on that,” “the guys who study these things,” etc. If the speaker realized they had used the word guys, they would justify by saying “and they’re actually all men,” as if that made it okay. That is actually &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a rule of thumb, I told someone at the Dagstuhl “if you can see the people in front of you, saying “guys” is okay. If you can’t see them, don’t use it.” This is perhaps an oversimplication, but it gets at that second-person (“you guys”) versus third-person (“those guys”) distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that women are underrepresented in STEM, and perhaps particularly in computer science (the Dagstuhl seminar I attended was about 20% female, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/961900236477169664&quot;&gt;seems to be the norm&lt;/a&gt;). Ed Yong outlines some of the issues in the beginning of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/02/i-spent-two-years-trying-to-fix-the-gender-imbalance-in-my-stories/552404/&quot;&gt;piece on increasing the diversity of scientists he quotes&lt;/a&gt;. To quote Ed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Women in science face a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/03/the-5-biases-pushing-women-out-of-stem&quot;&gt;gauntlet of well-documented systemic biases&lt;/a&gt;. They face long-standing stereotypes about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/01/six-year-old-girls-already-have-gendered-beliefs-about-intelligence/514340/&quot;&gt;their intelligence&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/scitable/content/does-gender-matter-by-ben-a-barres-10602856&quot;&gt;scientific acumen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2016/02/male-biology-students-underestimate-their-female-peers/462924/&quot;&gt;They need better college grades&lt;/a&gt; to get the same prestige as equally skilled men, they &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/109/41/16474.full&quot;&gt;receive less mentoring&lt;/a&gt;, they’re rated as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/109/41/16474.full&quot;&gt;less competent and less employable&lt;/a&gt; than equally qualified men, they’re less likely to be invited to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2017/12/women-are-invited-to-give-fewer-talks-than-men-at-top-us-universities/548657/&quot;&gt;give talks&lt;/a&gt;, they earn &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/inequality-quantified-mind-the-gender-gap-1.12550&quot;&gt;less than their male peers&lt;/a&gt;, and they have to deal with significant levels of &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/context-and-variation/safe13-field-site-chilly-climate-and-abuse/&quot;&gt;harassment and abuse&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you say “the guys at google,” you are erasing the women who work there, even if the people &lt;em&gt;you happen to know&lt;/em&gt; are all male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know lots of cool men, but when I talk about teams to my students (who are mostly female, because I work at a women’s college) I try to speak in gender neutral terms. If my students have heard me talk about “the people I know at google,” “the people I know at facebook,” “the people who work on the tidyverse,” etc., they can project themselves into that group. When they come to me for a contact at a company, and I put them in touch with a man, that feels incidental. I know lots of people, that contact just happened to be male. Plus, in between when I make those statements in class and when people follow up, teams often diversify and I meet more folks. So by starting with a gender-neutral, I’m leaving the door open for more diverse teams in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to hear about gender, I want to hear about the work. If you are going to reference a specific person, of course it is okay to indicate their gender and use their pronouns. But, if you’re going to speak about a group of two or more people in the third person, please try to remove the word “guys” from your vocabulary. We’re all people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;http://prestosketching.com/blog/2018/01/27/easy-ways-to-show-more-diversity-in-your-sketches/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/faces-hair.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Many diverse face sketches&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Image via &lt;a href=&quot;http://prestosketching.com/blog/2018/01/27/easy-ways-to-show-more-diversity-in-your-sketches/&quot;&gt;prestosketching&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 04:53:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/More-guys.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/More-guys.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/faces-hair.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Scientists Programming</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;At the Dagstuhl seminar, &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.cs.unlv.edu/stefika/&quot;&gt;Andreas Stefik&lt;/a&gt; asked me to speak about “Scientists Programming.” I’m not sure whether he did this on purpose, but by assigning people their talk titles, he drew us a little outside our comfort zone and got us to think more deeply. “Scientists Programming” wasn’t a talk that I had in my pocket, and wasn’t what I would have proposed, but it was fun to pull together. It made me realize that scientists programming is actually one of my primary interests, although I’ve never written that anywhere before. Felienne wrote up a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.felienne.com/archives/5900&quot;&gt;nice summary&lt;/a&gt; of my talk, but I wanted to write down some thoughts of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/clement127/15236140202/in/photolist-pdncEs-rabMJr-qSKYvp-qPeSji-rmJJdW-btryhH-qK7VJj-cm1Hb-qdaYpW-fWAdZ-9WhgHt-oLa2TT-2vuJD-2vuKd-mk1ib-qAU7wq-r3voVM-8CAcWc-9oggZ-7w3hnt-56tdL-oLa3fV-2vuPq-2vuJ5-oLqNAT-otW1FH-hGxPy-9Gbfpi-kyh6Q-wL7Y9q-anxVft-otW5n1-bWGa2P-qmxh8-otWG7V-nCpBGK-oLa2C2-pqcggk-61RzgT-dgrA8g-gbGJp-nBBqqg-anxVyP-6KVaRB-anAxnS-anxJWP-oJoZ4d-rcEdVP-aySHmX-anxJdr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/ScientistsProgramming.png&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Female lego scientist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the talk, I broke scientists’ programming tasks three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making models to generate data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generating data to make models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;application programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That first category would include any scientist who has a theory about the world, and using modeling to try to represent some relationship, then runs the model to generate data. Once you have that data, you compare it to what you’ve seen in the real world to see how good your model is. I’ve seen this done in ecology with predator/prey relationships, but I’m pretty sure physicists, chemists, and many others use this same technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second category is the one I think about the most, because it’s more statistical. In this paradigm, scientists generate data (through experimentation, surveying, observation, etc), and use those data to generate a model, which is likely statistical. Then, they assess how well the model does at representing the real world. I see these first two paradigms as two sides of the same coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final category, application programming, is the one I know the least about. I know some scientists do things like program a Raspberry Pi to do some specific sensor activity, or program a robot to explore in a deep cave. However, I think that this category is usually in service of one of the above two (scientists are usually trying to observe something about the world). Since application programming is outside of my expertise, and I knew it would be the most familiar to the group at the Dagstuhl, I didn’t discuss this in my talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;http://materials.dagstuhl.de/files/18/18061/18061.AmeliaA.McNamara1.Slides2.pdf&quot;&gt;see my slides&lt;/a&gt; if you want to know everything I covered, but the meat of the talk was digging into the paper by Julia Stewart Lowndes, et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-017-0160&quot;&gt;“Our path to better science in less time using open data science tools”&lt;/a&gt;. This paper is a perfect case study of a group of scientists who “We thought [they] were doing reproducible science” by using Excel, writing up their process, keeping versions of files by changing filenames, etc. But, they were able to transition to a more robust workflow using git/GitHub, R/RStudio, and RMarkdown. This has made them more accurate, and reduced the amount of time they spend on analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is crucial. Science is the source of a lot of the “ground truth” we rely on as a society. It determines which treatments get used by doctors, what interventions we try on the environment, and just our general knowledge of how the world works. If science is wrong, there are big implications. One common example are &lt;a href=&quot;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-016-1044-7&quot;&gt;Excel errors in genomics research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love that Lowndes’ group has made their code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OHI-Science/&quot;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. This is useful on so many levels&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone wanting to check their calculations can do so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are a scientist, you can use it as a reference for coding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming language designers can examine how scientists authentically code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my talk, I showed some arbitrarily-chosen code from their repo to display how the tidyverse syntax makes code more human-readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_indicator_mean_loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_indicator_mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;left_join&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_loc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; 
                                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;monitoring_area&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;station_cleaned&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_loc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_loc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DECWGSN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DECWGSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 31&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;64.207281&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 30&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;61.679815&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 29&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;59.705518&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 32&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;60.108130&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Rectangle 23 &amp;amp; 28&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;63.505817&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))),&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 31&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;23.511161&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 30&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;21.269112&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 29&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;21.264879&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;ICES SD 32&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;25.772410&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ifelse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Rectangle 23 &amp;amp; 28&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;21.351243&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                                 		&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;as.character&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station_cleaned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;as.character&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;station&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;temp_long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_scores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; 
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_area&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;core_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;taxa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;group_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;monitoring_area&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;core_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;taxa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gather&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ungroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;group_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;basin_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;core_indicator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope_mean_basin_indicator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;slope_mean_basin_taxa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ungroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;basin_n_obs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;coastal_fish_scores_long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; 
                            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;score_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;score1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; 
                            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Basin_HOLAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
                            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Basin_HOLAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the programming language designers found this code hard to read and confusing. Although I’ve heard computer scientists complain about R many times before, I wasn’t anticipating this. I thought that the piped sequence of function calls would be pretty readable. Maybe it was the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/code&gt; for the pipe rather than &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;, or maybe they would have preferred to see it as separate steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had shown this example, taken from Garrett Grolemund’s Master the Tidyverse materials (which I also showed in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmeliaMN/IntroToR&quot;&gt;Intro to R &amp;amp; RStudio&lt;/a&gt; workshop).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;year&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;year&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;boys_2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;babynames&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;year&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sex&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think with this comparison, it’s easier to see why the piped approach is better for people. With the nested function calls, you have to do a lot of checking in your head to make sure the parentheses are matched, and it’s hard to follow the logic. The incremental approach is good, but you type the name of the data many times. In the last example, the data flows through the piped sequence in a clearer way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question that came up in my talk was “if we fixed the problems with R as a language, would you appreciate that?” and I didn’t have a great answer. As a user, I (and I believe most scientists) don’t feel the language issues that frustrate computer scientists. It just works for what I need to do. In fact, my talk introduced yet another idea that we came back to again and again– some people who use programming languages don’t think of themselves as programmers. I know many people who use R, but consider it a tool to do data analysis rather than something to program in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the thing I exposed people to that they were most excited about was RMarkdown. While it seemed most people were familiar with the idea of iPython/Jupyter notebooks, they hadn’t seen knitr before. The idea that they could create a fully reproducible journal article interweaving text and code was very appealling. I showed a simple example with HTML output including text, code, and code output, but over the next few days I demoed more complex (Rnw) examples from my own work that produce publication-ready documents. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/COSTDataExpo2013/AmeliaMN/blob/master/PaperFinalDraft.pdf&quot;&gt;this pdf of a paper for Computational Statistics&lt;/a&gt; was generated from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/COSTDataExpo2013/AmeliaMN/blob/master/PaperFinalDraft.Rnw&quot;&gt;this LaTeX/knitr file&lt;/a&gt;. While this group of computer scientists work on experiments surrounding programming language design, and therefore do the same types of data analytic tasks as many scientists, they didn’t have this piece of their workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 03:43:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2018/02/11/Scientists-Programming.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/ScientistsProgramming.png" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>R syntax comparison</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;For my rstudio::conf working, Intro to R &amp;amp; RStudio, I finally finished my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rstudio/cheatsheets/raw/master/syntax.pdf&quot;&gt;cheatsheet on R syntaxes&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been working on this for at least a year (😱 ), so I’m glad to see it out in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I posted the cheatsheet online, I got some critical feedback, which I would like to address in the form of a FAQ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/rstudio/cheatsheets/raw/master/syntax.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.amelia.mn/img/SyntaxComparisonCheatsheet.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;R syntax comparison cheatsheet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why didn’t you include data.table syntax?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Mostly, because I don’t know &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data.table&lt;/code&gt;, so I wouldn’t have done a good job. Also, because I don’t know of anyone who is teaching data.table to absolute novices. However, if someone wanted to generate all the analogous tasks (summary statistics, plots, wrangling) in data.table and share them, I would be very interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why did you use the word “syntax” when that’s not quite precise?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Because that is a word commonly associated with programming languages. While these three paradigms may not be precisely three different syntaxes, they are certainly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syntactic_sugar&quot;&gt;syntactic sugar&lt;/a&gt; or idioms within the language. I often refer to them as like accents within a human language. If you were learning English, you wouldn’t try to learn it with a British accent, an accent from the American South, and an accent from Australia. You’d learn it one way, and be able to recognize other accents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why didn’t you express [x] in this more efficient way?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; This usually comes up because of my use of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tapply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cyl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;efficient&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;if_else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TRUE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FALSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-r&quot; data-lang=&quot;r&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mtcars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mutate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;efficient&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;if_else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mpg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both of these cases, I was erring on the side of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a) more verbosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;b) a more general pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, although I learned R long before the tidyverse existed, I never got adept at the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apply()&lt;/code&gt; family of functions. Every time I needed to use one, it was a fall down a rabbithole of “tapply? sapply? mapply?” (In fact, trying to create that tapply call for this post included just such a search.) While I would encourage people coding within the base R paradigm to learn these functions, I think the three-line version is easier to think through, and represents a much more common “style” that you will see on places like StackOverflow. In many cases, there is no &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; equivalent, and you end up doing this sort of repetitive writing of the dataset name and nesting of statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mutate()&lt;/code&gt; call, even though it was unnecessary to include the TRUE and FALSE, I knew that it would provide a better pattern for students who wanted to make their own variables. If you want &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;efficient&lt;/code&gt; to instead be “yes” and “no” character strings, you can just sub “yes” for TRUE and “no” for FALSE, without having to think about the magic that goes with logicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Why didn’t you show ggformula or the formula-based base R plots?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; I did! They’re just on the back of the sheet. I don’t feel like &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ggformula/index.html&quot;&gt;ggformula&lt;/a&gt; is a full-fledged graphics library yet, so I don’t want to present it as such. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;base&lt;/code&gt; graphics, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lattice&lt;/code&gt; graphics and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; graphics are all full libraries, so I used those on the front of the sheet. As for formula-based base R plots, I think they are much less common online. My main use case for this cheatsheet is to give to students who I am teaching one particular syntax. For example, I used to teach completely in the formula syntax, but have switched to tidyverse syntax. However, sometimes when I demo code I switch to another syntax because it feels more natural for the task. Or, students google something and find code from another syntax. The cheatsheet serves as a grounding device to say, this is just another way to express the same idea I am familiar with. Since I (almost) never teach base R, I include it on the cheatsheet mostly as a foil to my argument that the tidyverse is more human-readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have other questions? Ask me in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 02:43:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/02/11/Syntax-comparison.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/teaching/2018/02/11/Syntax-comparison.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/SyntaxComparisonCheatsheet.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>On microaggressions</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was glad to see Karl Broman’s blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/12/18/these-guys/&quot;&gt;a troubling conference talk&lt;/a&gt;. In the post, Karl describes how the speaker repeatedly used the word “guys” to describe people involved in statistics, and how he and Hadley Wickham reached out to him in an effort to get him to change his ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were in the room during the talk, I’m sure the experience is still viscerally available to you, but for those who were not, I think Karl’s post falls far short of the necessary description to underscore the problem. As I said in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/942962475418505216&quot;&gt;recent tweet&lt;/a&gt;, it’s hard to convey in words how icky the talk was. But, I’m going to make an attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk was part of a session &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2016/onlineprogram/ActivityDetails.cfm?SessionID=212769&quot;&gt;honoring Bill Cleveland&lt;/a&gt;. Other talks in the session were fantastic– in particular, Di Cook’s talk, where she &lt;a href=&quot;http://visiphilia.org/2016/08/03/CM-hierarchy&quot;&gt;replicated Cleveland and McGill’s findings live&lt;/a&gt; (!!). But this particular speaker, who has now &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-12-16/google-researcher-accused-of-sexual-harassment-roiling-ai-field&quot;&gt;come under scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@kristianlum/statistics-we-have-a-problem-304638dc5de5&quot;&gt;sexual harassment&lt;/a&gt;, gave a talk that was broadly derisive and dismissive of anyone who is not a white man pursuing statistics. I have a record of many of the comments he made as part of email threads from the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a talk that included “data science” in the title, he was dismissive of data science, making the comparison that statistics is like architecture (accompanied by a photo of the Sydney Opera House) while data science is like cookie-cutter tract housing (accompanied by a photo of a suburban development), managing to be derisive of both manual labor and the efforts of many of the people in the audience.  He disparaged useR, saying that you should only go if you want to hear about “guys who made a nice plot.” The entire tenor of the talk was that work with data is less important than statistics, a completely bizarre take in a talk supposedly honoring Bill Cleveland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, the speaker made it clear by his references, language, and tone, that he only considers contributions by men. Every researcher he mentioned by name was male (even though he was speaking shortly after Di Cook, clearly eminent in the field). This might seem like a justification for his gendered language, but I think it speaks to a deeper issue– he simply does not see contributions by women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious indicator of his dismissal of women was his repetitive use of the word “guys,” as Karl has mentioned. The usage become more and more grating throughout the talk, but even on his first use of the word the colleague sitting to my left said “sexist” under her breath at the same time I corrected “people” under mine. On twitter, many people chimed in to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/760881386651848708&quot;&gt;Karl’s tweet at the time&lt;/a&gt; saying they found the comments jarring as well. In situations where he could easily have said “people,” “statisticians,” “data scientists,” “programmers,” or many other gender-neutral terms, the speaker always used the word “guys.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes this difficult to adequately describe is that in some contexts, “guys” is almost gender-neutral. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/12/27/guys-guys-guys/&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidjayharris/status/760933065950629888&quot;&gt;Dave Harris linked&lt;/a&gt; suggests that “guys” is only gender-neutral if you say “you guys.” Phrases like “we’re going to need to hire a Python guy” or “I met a great Erlang guy” were perceived by the majority &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be gender-neutral. As Karl responded to someone saying she didn’t care about the use of “guys” as long as she was not excluded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;in this context, you would have cared.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Karl Broman (@kwbroman) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/760922466894114816?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what is so insidious about these types of microaggressions. When you try to describe them, they sound insignificant, even though for those who were present it was clear there was a pattern of dismissal. It was so blatant that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;steam was literally coming out of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@AmeliaMN&lt;/a&gt;’s ears&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Hadley Wickham (@hadleywickham) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hadleywickham/status/760882186551697409?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’m _still_ shaking with rage. Literally.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Karl Broman (@kwbroman) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kwbroman/status/760885433941319680?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, it was clear that some action needed to be taken. Through email, Karl, Hadley, Hilary Parker (looped in for her interest in the issue, although she wasn’t present at the talk) and I discussed that while the talk offended us personally, it wasn’t a clear-cut violation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2016/conductpolicy.cfm&quot;&gt;JSM’s Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt;. This left making a comment to him, either publicly or privately. I knew that I (as a junior, female, data science-y person) would get no respect from him, so I encouraged Karl and Hadley to call him out. The speaker had mentioned Hadley in his talk, and since both of them are more senior, male, and ASA Fellows, I hoped their words would carry some weight. Karl, Hadley, Hilary and I went back and forth via email working on drafts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, we ended up softening the language in successive drafts. A first draft said people “were taken aback, to the point of being offended,” while the final version just says “were taken aback.” Karl initially mentioned that he “might also talk about the pedestrian carpenter data scientist vs the soaring architect applied statistician, but two criticisms without any positive comments seems too much.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a week, the email Karl &lt;a href=&quot;http://kbroman.org/blog/2017/12/18/these-guys/&quot;&gt;reproduced on his blog&lt;/a&gt; was sent, and after a couple months I followed up with Karl to see if the speaker had responded. He hadn’t, and we dropped the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regret that I didn’t feel comfortable writing publicly about this at the time, and that I didn’t push harder for follow-up when I heard he had ignored the email. We now know this particular person has a (alleged) history of sexual harassment, and perhaps publicizing this talk would have opened the issue up earlier. As Mara tweeted,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Reason number 247 &amp;quot;just send an email, we&amp;#39;re all adults here&amp;quot; is operationally disastrous advice. Also, and a whole host of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RLadiesGlobal?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@RLadiesGlobal&lt;/a&gt; can back me up on this, sometimes communicating privately is the OPPOSITE of a good idea!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mara Averick (@dataandme) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dataandme/status/943085039897718785?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 19, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the #metoo movement in general and the recent attention on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@kristianlum/statistics-we-have-a-problem-304638dc5de5&quot;&gt;harassment in statistics, data science, and machine learning&lt;/a&gt; in particular, I am reminded of the Brandeis quote that “Sunlight is said to be the best of disinfectants.” Of course, this is only true if people believe the stories that are voiced, but we seem to be at a watershed moment. I regret not shining more light on this at the time, and hope that we can be more open about violations of community norms, even if they seem “minor.” They could be indicative of a larger pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2017/12/19/On-Microaggressions.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.amelia.mn/blog/conferences/2017/12/19/On-Microaggressions.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="https://www.amelia.mn/img/grr.png" />
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>