<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
	<channel>
		<title>Amelia McNamara</title>
		<description>Personal website of Amelia McNamara, statistical and data sciences professor at Smith College.</description>		
		<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Fitbit colors</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have been a devoted Fitbit user for over a year now, and I think that as a device it is the sort of thing that a statistician would natually enjoy. It produces rich data about my day-to-day life, can be used to identify notable dates in my year, and does a great job of making me more physically active &amp;quot;on the margin.&amp;quot; But, the Fitbit app designers have made very strange color choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d appreciate any insight you have about why they might have chosen these colors. Here&amp;#39;s the daily trajectory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get up and start moving, the graphs show your steps in an aqua blue that is very similar to the Fitbit dashboard color. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/Fitbit1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At the beginning of the day&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, as you continue, the colors move from aqua, to yellow, to orange/red. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/Fitbit2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A little later&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/Fitbit3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Getting close to the step goal&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when you hit your step goal the color switches to green,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/Fitbit4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Goal reached&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This color progression drives me a little crazy. It&amp;#39;s not in rainbow order, and it seems like it should move from red to orange, to yellow, to green/blue. In other words, the colors should indicate something about your health level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another choice I can imagine for the colors would be to code the progression I mentioned above to the progress you&amp;#39;ve made over the day. The Fitbit knows how long your typical day is, and it knows when you woke up. Maybe it could show green if you were making good progress to your goal for the day (given the time of day it was), yellow if you weren&amp;#39;t, and red if you were really behind. Then, once you hit the goal it could switch to a different color (e.g. purple) to indicate you&amp;#39;d hit it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any ideas about the color trajectory they&amp;#39;ve chosen? Do other fitness trackers use similar colors?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/visualization/2015/01/14/FitbitColors.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/visualization/2015/01/14/FitbitColors.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/Fitbit1.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Fabric posters</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t you hate having to take a poster to conferences? The tube is bulky, it&amp;#39;s easy to forget in the airport (or on the plane!), sometimes you get charged extra for your &amp;quot;additional carry-on&amp;quot; and often the poster doesn&amp;#39;t look great once it arrives. Plus, it&amp;#39;s expensive to print a poster, and you usually only get one use out of it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter, the fabric poster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;I learned about this wonderful option via twitter, before the Women in Statistics Conference. I was one of three women to bring fabric posters. Shown here are the other two, demonstrating one of the fantastic things about fabric posters-- they&amp;#39;re flexible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superhero statisticians to the rescue! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kralljr&quot;&gt;@kralljr&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/HelenPowell01&quot;&gt;@HelenPowell01&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/WiS2014?src=hash&quot;&gt;#WiS2014&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/uuVl05d40z&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/uuVl05d40z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stephanie Hicks (@stephaniehicks) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stephaniehicks/status/467447722703060994&quot;&gt;May 16, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better than that, you can fold them up in your suitcase and they don&amp;#39;t wrinkle (or if they do, you can iron them!). Plus, they have the same DPI as paper, they&amp;#39;re cheaper, and you can easily re-use them (either as a poster or as a superhero cape). Still not sold? Check out these photos from IEEE Vis in Paris. The conference organizers needed to take down the posters quickly, and almost anyone with a paper poster ended up with something ripped, wrinkled, and taped to someone else&amp;#39;s poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN&quot;&gt;@AmeliaMN&lt;/a&gt; Sad paper posters, happy (folded) fabric poster. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ieeevis?src=hash&quot;&gt;#ieeevis&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/VFZj2HdOuH&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/VFZj2HdOuH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/533186832344055809&quot;&gt;November 14, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so how do you do it? &lt;a href=&quot;http://ascb.org/how-to-print-a-fabric-poster/&quot;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; is fantastic, and it&amp;#39;s where I learned how to print a fabric poster. For whatever reason, that link keeps changing, so I&amp;#39;ll summarize the main points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use the website &lt;a href=&quot;www.spoonflower.com&quot;&gt;spoonflower.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;choose the &amp;quot;performance knit&amp;quot; fabric, which should cost around $25&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upload your poster &lt;strong&gt;as a png&lt;/strong&gt; (ignore at your peril!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make sure it looks right, and order!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Printing and shipping is variable, but Spoonflower has a data-driven page that will tell you &lt;a href=&quot;http://help.spoonflower.com/customer/portal/articles/1173283-how-long-will-it-take-to-get-my-order-&quot;&gt;how many days production is currently taking&lt;/a&gt;. If you need your poster quickly, you can pay for rush shipping, but either way the poster will come folded up in one of those soft plastic envelopes that fits easily into any mailbox. What are you waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2014/12/12/FabricPosters.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2014/12/12/FabricPosters.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/IEEEVisPoster.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New tools for data analysis and journalism</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;a href=&quot;http://symposium2014.computation-and-journalism.com/&quot;&gt;Computation + Journalism Symposium&lt;/a&gt; continues to be filled with fascinating inlets to journalistic projects and innovative computational approaches (like using drones to map garbage dumps) the component that always catches my attention is the demoing of new tools for data analysis. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year&amp;#39;s symposium was hosted at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://brown.columbia.edu/&quot;&gt;Brown Institute&lt;/a&gt; and was no exception-- I saw many projects that approached elements of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/%7Eamcnamara/FOSP.html&quot;&gt;theory about the future of statistical programming&lt;/a&gt; from different directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the data analysis projects were discussed on a panel about journalistic platforms. The panelists were&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/gideonmann/&quot;&gt;Gideon Mann&lt;/a&gt;, of Bloomberg, speaking about &lt;a href=&quot;https://colaboratory.jupyter.org/welcome/&quot;&gt;coLaboratory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kareemamin.com/&quot;&gt;Kareem Amin&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a href=&quot;http://newscorp.com/&quot;&gt;NewsCorp&lt;/a&gt;, talking about a forthcoming tool that uses custom HTML tags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://brianabelson.com/&quot;&gt;Brian Abelson&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a href=&quot;http://enigma.io/&quot;&gt;enigma.io&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://towcenter.org/&quot;&gt;Tow Center&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&quot;http://nytlabs.github.io/streamtools/&quot;&gt;streamtools&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nytlabs.com/&quot;&gt;NYT R&amp;amp;D labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the tools spoke to the ideas I am engaging with in my dissertation, which I found very encouraging. The context that I have been thinking most deeply about is the high school data science classroom, much like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/%7Eamcnamara/mobilize.html&quot;&gt;Mobilize&lt;/a&gt; project, which I formerly worked on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, data journalism is the other context that I had been hoping to find relevance in. The fact that the panelists were engaging with the same issues, of being able to get started quickly but develop new modules as needed, of publishability and the need for interactivity, suggests that the two seemingly-different contexts (high school students/teachers, and data journalists) might not be that different in their needs after all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;coLaboratory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had asked my twitterverse about coLaboratory in September,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saw this article on CoLaboratory, &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/MylVNfZckI&quot;&gt;http://t.co/MylVNfZckI&lt;/a&gt; but would love to hear from people who use it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hmason&quot;&gt;@hmason&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amelia McNamara (@AmeliaMN) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AmeliaMN/status/515557079642169344&quot;&gt;September 26, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but got no response except for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hmason&quot;&gt;Hilary Mason&lt;/a&gt; responding that she didn&amp;#39;t know the project and didn&amp;#39;t know why her photo was used on the article. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it was great to hear about the project straight from the horse&amp;#39;s mouth. &lt;a href=&quot;https://colaboratory.jupyter.org/welcome/&quot;&gt;coLaboratory&lt;/a&gt; seems to be part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;project Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;, and it offers an iPython notebook that allows you to collaborate with others. Sadly, all their documentation seems to be technical, without any of the &amp;quot;so what&amp;quot; that I look for when learning about a tool. I did find a google research &lt;a href=&quot;http://googleresearch.blogspot.com/2014/08/doing-data-science-with-colaboratory.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; which gives a little more context and a few examples. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, coLaboratory can produce interactive reports (meaning, with sliders and buttons for users to interact with). It also has some focus on making it easy to develop the interface, using simple commands to invoke interactive controls. However, once a user modifies a control they need to re-click on the &amp;quot;run&amp;quot; button to see the updated information. This is my main complaint with iPython notebooks in general, so it&amp;#39;s too bad that the version for creating interactive documents doesn&amp;#39;t manage to jump that hurdle.  The other problem is that the source code really isn&amp;#39;t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; readable when you get down to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thelma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool that Amin was talking about had different advantages. First, it is a click-driven interface, so you click on data inputs and outputs and see the results in the browser. By allowing users to build analysis in this way, you make it easier for novices to get started easily while still making nice results. The product he was talking about is based on custom HTML tags, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.polymer-project.org/&quot;&gt;Polymer&lt;/a&gt; web components. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t think that Amin wanted the name of the project to be made public yet, but he showed a demo and several people tweeted out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thelmanews.github.io/thelma-component-demo/data-demo.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you do data analysis it updates the webpage: &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/isWky1uNAV&quot;&gt;http://t.co/isWky1uNAV&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kareemamin&quot;&gt;@kareemamin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/cj2014?src=hash&quot;&gt;#cj2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nick Diakopoulos (@ndiakopoulos) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ndiakopoulos/status/525677010816090112&quot;&gt;October 24, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and it appears to be called Thelma. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, Thelma needs a lot more work before it&amp;#39;s really made public. It&amp;#39;s not clear how to begin if you want to do something that doesn&amp;#39;t use the data and chart types already on the demo page, and even those aren&amp;#39;t exactly transparent. But, there&amp;#39;s a lot of potential here. The resulting charts are somewhat interactive, and updating happens as soon as you modify the inputs/outputs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;streamtools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, &lt;a href=&quot;http://brianabelson.com/&quot;&gt;Brian Abelson&lt;/a&gt; spoke about &lt;a href=&quot;http://nytlabs.github.io/streamtools/&quot;&gt;streamtools&lt;/a&gt;. Abelson was not involved with the development of streamtools, but he found it useful enough that he was willing to be its advocate on the panel. streamtools is a dataflow programming environment for working with live streaming data. Rather than waiting for data to be presented as a flat file, the lab wanted to allow users to deal directly with data as it streams in. Since I work with the Communications Design Group, it immediately made me think of Dan Ingalls&amp;#39; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fabrik_(software)&quot;&gt;fabrik&lt;/a&gt; (a visual programming environment in which users &amp;quot;wired&amp;quot; components together), but of course there is a rich history of this sort of blocks programming environments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool does a great job of making explicit the links between components in the system, and giving a visual hint to the data flowing through the system. However, it seems that the intended user of the system is someone who knows quite a bit about data analysis and programming. The blocks do not cue you toward their behavior, and the &amp;quot;parts bin&amp;quot; (to steal a &lt;a href=&quot;http://lively-web.org/welcome.html&quot;&gt;Lively&lt;/a&gt; term) is full of consise but not extremely descriptive labels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IEEE programming language rating&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other project (not from the panel) that caught my eye was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nickdiakopoulos.com/&quot;&gt;Nick Diakopoulos&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39; interactive &lt;a href=&quot;http://spectrum.ieee.org/computing/software/top-10-programming-languages&quot;&gt;ranking of programming languages&lt;/a&gt; for IEEE Spectrum. Sadly, it seems like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://spectrum.ieee.org/static/interactive-the-top-programming-languages&quot;&gt;interactive version&lt;/a&gt; is behind a paywall, but it&amp;#39;s worth the 99¢ to see it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ranking is based on a number of factors, such as position in google results, number of github repositories, and questions on stackoverflow. The interactive tool lets you see four different versions of the rating: IEEE Spectrum, Trending, Jobs, and Open. You can also filter the languages shown to only display Mobile, Web, Enterprise, or Embedded languages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real beauty in this project is that you can manipulate the parameters used in the rankings to create your own version. If you don&amp;#39;t believe that google page rank is a good measure of a programming language&amp;#39;s ubiquity, you can drag that slider down or even zero it out. This lets you modify the procedure used to create the ranking, and it allows you to perform ad hoc sensitivity analysis. Many changes to parameters do not change the rankings, which could make a reader more confident in the ranking as provided by the IEEE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the list is so robust to parameter manipulation that it was hard for me to tell if the ranking was being updated dynamically, or if you need to click the &amp;quot;Save as Custom&amp;quot; button to see the results! However, they do provide a great &amp;quot;Make a Comparison&amp;quot; button, which shows a sort of slopegraph/bumps chart (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edwardtufte.com/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg?msg_id=0003nk&quot;&gt;Tufte&lt;/a&gt;) displaying which languages were displaced and to where.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article/interactive can&amp;#39;t really be described as a &amp;quot;tool,&amp;quot; per se, but I loved seeing an example of analysis where the underlying data work was exposed. This is the sort of &amp;quot;interaction all the way down&amp;quot; that I think is the future of data analysis. Not only should creators of data products be able to interact with their work as they produce it, consumers of those products should have the opportunity to deeply critique the process by viewing a transparent representation of the analysis process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so invigorated by everything that I saw at the symposium. It&amp;#39;s such a treat to be around people who are thinking about some of the same issues that I am. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about any of these projects, they are almost all forkable on github, which is another one of the principles that I think all good software should adhere to! What other interesting projects have you seen recently?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2014/10/27/New-tools-for-data.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2014/10/27/New-tools-for-data.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/2014-10-27 10.10.06.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Kid Pix</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Since a lot of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la&quot;&gt;datascience.la&lt;/a&gt; meetups are held at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crosscamp.us/&quot;&gt;Cross Campus&lt;/a&gt;, I joined their newletter, and I&amp;#39;m so glad I did-- it leads me to all sorts of cool things! One such event was a talk by &lt;a href=&quot;http://red-green-blue.com/about/&quot;&gt;Craig Hickman&lt;/a&gt; about the history and success of &lt;a href=&quot;http://red-green-blue.com/kid-pix-the-early-years/&quot;&gt;Kid Pix&lt;/a&gt;. If you weren&amp;#39;t a child in the &amp;#39;90s, Kid Pix was a fabulously open-ended paint program designed for kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk was a great mix of nostalgia and inspiration for me. I loved hearing about the principles that guided Hickman as he worked, like the idea of contextual menus, so kids never had to look in the menu bar. I was also brought back to my childhood, creating artwork, menus for pretend restaurants, birthday cards, notes, and much more, all in Kid Pix. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hickman referenced two papers that inspired him-- &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/stream/byte-magazine-1983-12/1983_12_BYTE_08-12_Easy_Software#page/n143/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Walt Disney and User Oriented Software&lt;/a&gt; and Alan Kay&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://frameworker.files.wordpress.com/2008/05/alan-kay-computer-software-sciam-sept-84.pdf&quot;&gt;Computer Software&lt;/a&gt;. Since I work with Alan, I&amp;#39;ve read Computer Software several times, and love the ideas about software being flexible enough to do things that the designer didn&amp;#39;t foresee, and the importance of computer users &amp;quot;creating&amp;quot; rather than just &amp;quot;using&amp;quot; (something that comes up a lot in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/%7Eamcnamara/Mobilize.html&quot;&gt;Mobilize project&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I hadn&amp;#39;t seen the article on Disney before. When I read it, I was surprised to discover I had heard most of the anecdotes before from people in Alan&amp;#39;s group. The article is full of connections between the principles of Disney animators and how they could be applied by software developers. For example, &amp;quot;prepare the audience.&amp;quot; A Disney character will show you what it&amp;#39;s going to do before it begins the action-- for example, by bending its knees before a jump. Software should do the same. The author suggests that a slow in/slow out approach to changing things on the screen can help a user be prepared for what is happening, and not get lost in a transition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kid Pix accomplished a lot of the goals outlined in these two papers. You could see the tools available to you on the left hand side, and you always knew to expect relevant contextual options to appear at the bottom of the screen. Everything was modifiable, including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_Kare&quot;&gt;Susan Kare&lt;/a&gt;-designed font stamps. Hickman explained that he&amp;#39;d loved the hieroglyphic-style font &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kare.com/portfolio/05_apple_fonts.html&quot;&gt;Cairo&lt;/a&gt;, designed by Kare for the original Macintosh, so he just &amp;quot;put it back&amp;quot; as the stamps you could use in Kid Pix. As a child, I loved the fact that the stamps were modifiable, and I think the goal of a program that is manipulable all the way down is wonderful for any age level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the unique qualities of Kid Pix, compared to a more standard paint program, is that the process matters as much or more than the final product. Although this had been my experience as a kid, I hadn&amp;#39;t realized that it was explicitly intended to be that way. Listen to Hickman explain,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;http://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F170212262&amp;show_artwork=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original version of Kid Pix was black and white, but Hickman soon created a second version with the software company Broderbund, which was in color and included sounds. This is the version I have the strongest memories of, although I think we had the black-and-white version first. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was struck by David Pogue&amp;#39;s review of commercial version, which Hickman showed us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kid Pix 1.0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros: Brilliant; hilarious; innovative; inexpensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cons: None. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that gives you something to aspire to, doesn&amp;#39;t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ever used Kid Pix, its sounds will immediately bring you back. Here is Hickman demoing some of the tools, including the popular eraser bomb tool that cleared the entire screen:
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;http://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F170212261&amp;show_artwork=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to try out the original (black and white) Kid Pix, James Friend has created a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jamesfriend.com.au/pce-js/&quot;&gt;Mac emulator&lt;/a&gt; that runs it. For Hickman&amp;#39;s complete talk, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LqVhK6JgbSU&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; from Media Leaders or &lt;a href=&quot;http://red-green-blue.com/kid-pix-the-early-years/&quot;&gt;Hickman&amp;#39;s page on Kid Pix&lt;/a&gt;, which goes through a lot of the material from his talk. Thanks again to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crosscamp.us/&quot;&gt;Cross Campus&lt;/a&gt; for hosting such a great event! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/tools/2014/10/01/KidPix.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/tools/2014/10/01/KidPix.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/CraigHickman.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Data Science LA</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m now involved in the recently-launched &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la&quot;&gt;datascience.la&lt;/a&gt; blog. While you&amp;#39;ll probably be drawn to the site for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/category/user-conference/sessions/&quot;&gt;useR! conference session videos&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/category/user-conference/interviews/&quot;&gt;interviews with data scientists&lt;/a&gt;, and meetup announcements, there&amp;#39;s going to be much more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/datascienceLA.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;DataScienceLA&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve posted &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/data-science-goes-to-college-with-datafest/&quot;&gt;Data Science Goes to College with DataFest&lt;/a&gt;, yet another summary of the yearly DataFest we hold at UCLA and that&amp;#39;s going national. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/statistics-grad-school-what-is-it-really-like/&quot;&gt;Statistics Grad School-- What is it Really Like?&lt;/a&gt; describing some of the experience of getting a PhD in statistics at UCLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;#39;ll be giving a talk at this month&amp;#39;s DataVis LA meetup, &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/datavis-la-meetup-eyeo-festival-highlights-august-26/&quot;&gt;Eyeo Festival Highlights&lt;/a&gt; on August 26th. Come by Cornerstone OnDemand to hear me talk about the things that inspired me the most from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://eyeofestival.com/&quot;&gt;eyeo festival&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to keep up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la&quot;&gt;datascience.la&lt;/a&gt;, you can follow along via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wwwDSLA&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/DataScienceLA&quot;&gt;youtube&lt;/a&gt;, add us to your favorite &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la/feed&quot;&gt;rss&lt;/a&gt; reader, or just drop by &lt;a href=&quot;http://datascience.la&quot;&gt;the site&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m excited to be a part of it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/teaching/2014/08/14/DataScienceLA.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/teaching/2014/08/14/DataScienceLA.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/datascienceLA.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>ICOTS discussion on technology in statistics education</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most interesting sessions I attended at ICOTS was the panel session, &lt;a href=&quot;http://icots.info/9/session.php?s=9H&quot;&gt;Future trends for technology in statistics education&lt;/a&gt;. The panel was chaired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/showperson?firstname=Chris&amp;amp;surname=Wild&quot; title=&quot;Chris Wild&quot;&gt;Chris Wild&lt;/a&gt; of Auckland, and featured&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;Deb Nolan&lt;/a&gt;, UC Berkeley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;Nick Horton&lt;/a&gt;, Smith College&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;Bill Finzer&lt;/a&gt;, Common Online Data Analysis Platform (CODAP)/Fathom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.tamu.edu/%7Ewest/&quot; title=&quot;Webster West&quot;&gt;Webster West&lt;/a&gt;, Texas A&amp;amp;M/StatCrunch. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I was so fascinated by the discussion, I ended up creating an almost-complete transcript of the discussion (biased by my personal interests, of course). I thought it was possible that someone else might be interested in my transcript, so I&amp;#39;m posting it here. Beyond my own interest bias, I&amp;#39;m sure that I&amp;#39;ve mis-attributed an idea here and there. Please let me know if there&amp;#39;s something I should change to be closer to the truth!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/2014-07-17 15.44.54-1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;The panel&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The panelists helping attendees find the last few seats (eventually, it was standing-room only)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question posed to the panel by Chris Wild was &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what do you consider the most exciting developments in technology for statistics education?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.tamu.edu/%7Ewest/&quot; title=&quot;Webster West&quot;&gt;WW&lt;/a&gt;: Student centered data collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;NH&lt;/a&gt;: Open source tools, giving more students access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: The recognition that data science as essential, and technology making it possible to integrate it into the whole curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: The popularity of data science and interest by students. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that question, the discussion really just moved to a more fluid form, where panelists fed off each other&amp;#39;s comments and moved the conversation forward. Here are some of the comments that caught my ear. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;NH&lt;/a&gt;: There isn&amp;#39;t going to be one &amp;quot;intro course,&amp;quot; there will be many courses. A second course needs to cover thinking with data, data wrangling, data munging (or whatever you call it). Hadley&amp;#39;s stuff is good, and uses simple verbs. Students should have the ability to do something with real world data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: Students need to be exposed to more than one technology. Don&amp;#39;t just turn the R crank. [At some point in the discussion, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt; shared that students often call her statistical computing course &amp;quot;the R course,&amp;quot; which makes her cringe.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.tamu.edu/%7Ewest/&quot; title=&quot;Webster West&quot;&gt;WW&lt;/a&gt;: I struggle to come up with the right verbs (for describing the tasks students need to be able to do, especially in terms of code). But, we all do. Maybe it&amp;#39;s better to start with examples. Visualize point A, point B, see how to do it, and then determine what skills are needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;quot;Data immersion&amp;quot; is an experience everyone should have, regardless of discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question arose here, perhaps raised by Chris Wild. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the advantages and disadvantages of menu-driven paradigms versus programming?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.tamu.edu/%7Ewest/&quot; title=&quot;Webster West&quot;&gt;WW&lt;/a&gt;: I write code that helps people do menu-driven things. Many teachers are unreachable when it comes to code, and menu-driven can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: There&amp;#39;s a difference between coding and scripting. Scripting is simpler, coding is more complex. To code, you need some understanding of control flow, etc. Scripting is more interacting at the console. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: In Fathom, you have a collection, and you can sample from it. That&amp;#39;s essentially a loop. If you&amp;#39;re going to be a data scientist, you need to think computationally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;NH&lt;/a&gt;: We need to think developmentally. Think about when parents are upset because they can&amp;#39;t toilet train their baby. You say, I&amp;#39;m confident by the time they&amp;#39;re 18, they&amp;#39;ll be okay. Then work backward from there. [Ed: I&amp;#39;ve lost what this analogy was supposed to be about. Is the baby a statistics student, and the toilet-training teaching them to code? Insights on this one would be appreciated].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coding lets you document your workflow. It&amp;#39;s much harder to do this in an interface. This helps with reproducibility, which we&amp;#39;ve basically decided is a good thing. Down the line, you want peer reviewers to be able to look at your data and code. Biologists have lab notebooks, that helps them be reproducible, and they see this in courses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: Ubiquitous data computing is coming. Imagine your Personal Data Calculator. Just like you always have something to write with, you will have a PDC. Technology for working with data will be just as pervasive as other technologies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;NH&lt;/a&gt;: Shiny lets me quickly make an applet that would take 6 months for a Java developer. There&amp;#39;s a speed up in the creation of tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.tamu.edu/%7Ewest/&quot; title=&quot;Webster West&quot;&gt;WW&lt;/a&gt;: In StatCrunch, I want to let textbook authors script their own applets (versus scripting artisanal applets for each author individually). This is coming down the road. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: In the past, I&amp;#39;ve tried making education games. One was a hospital that you tour around in. This effort was in Java, but we didn&amp;#39;t have the manpower. I had ideas about interactive dynamic documents, same thing. Shiny is making a difference, although I would prefer to be &amp;quot;down one level.&amp;quot; There&amp;#39;s a difference between dynamic and interactive-- dynamic means that output is automatically created for you from code. Interactive means that a reader can play with sliders, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: [Paraphrasing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;] &amp;quot;So, a learning technology is something that will be out of date in 10 years?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stat.auckland.ac.nz/showperson?firstname=Chris&amp;amp;surname=Wild&quot; title=&quot;Chris Wild&quot;&gt;Chris Wild&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there&amp;#39;s a design problem (that&amp;#39;s always the same) and an implementation problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;NH&lt;/a&gt;: Michael Bulmer&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://escholarship.org/uc/item/2q0740hv&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Island&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a big thing to take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: You can bring design in through simulation studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.smith.edu/%7Enhorton/&quot; title=&quot;Nick Horton&quot;&gt;NH&lt;/a&gt;: Looking at health services research: they use non-random data (e.g. from billings) to find out things about health. This is much the same as the problem we&amp;#39;re facing now. This is what we should be aiming for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: There&amp;#39;s a lot of room to grow in computer science at the high school level. This will change what we do at the college level.
&amp;quot;Have you heard about R.N. Jesus?&amp;quot; Stands for Random Number Generator, but you pray to it to get good numbers in a game. WoW is a super polished game. We don&amp;#39;t have the skills to build something polished like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time around here, the panel was opened up to questions from the audience. I&amp;#39;m not sure exactly what point that was. Nonethless, there was another question for the panel-- &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what will we be talking about at ICOTS 10 in 2018?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: There will be learning log data available. I hope statistics ed people will be using this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, someone (maybe &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.ucla.edu/%7Ergould/Home/About_Me.html&quot;&gt;Rob Gould&lt;/a&gt;) proposed a definition for Data Science. From my understanding of the comment, I sketched a Venn diagram in my notes which looked something like this:
&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/DataScience.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Data Science Venn Diagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An audience member suggested &lt;a href=&quot;coderdojo.com&quot;&gt;CoderDojo&lt;/a&gt; as a resource for students, which makes it cool to code, says every kid can code. [Ed: I think these types of claims are usually very limited to kids with a lot of privilege]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calvin.edu/%7Erpruim/&quot;&gt;Randy Pruim&lt;/a&gt; asked the panel, &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is there a dark side to this? Now, anyone can make a pretty graph, but it might not mean anything. There are thinking skills that are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/%7Enolan/&quot; title=&quot;Deb Nolan&quot;&gt;DN&lt;/a&gt;: We&amp;#39;ve always had this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.tamu.edu/%7Ewest/&quot; title=&quot;Webster West&quot;&gt;WW&lt;/a&gt;: We should be doing things like text analysis in intro classes. Students get out of intro classes, they think data is just numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cadrek12.org/users/william-finzer&quot; title=&quot;Bill Finzer&quot;&gt;BF&lt;/a&gt;: Personal data should be meaningful to individuals. It should be able to be worked with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with that, my transcript ends. See, I told you it might only be interesting to me! Those who were there, what insights did I neglect to capture? &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/teaching/2014/08/06/ICOTS-Panel-Transcript.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/teaching/2014/08/06/ICOTS-Panel-Transcript.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/2014-07-17 15.44.54-1.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Yes, and...</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of my primary teaching techniques is the improv-inspired &amp;quot;yes and...&amp;quot; move. People who have been trained in improvisational comedy know that the first rule is always to build on what your fellow performers say. If someone says, &amp;quot;now we&amp;#39;re sitting in a cafe, having coffee&amp;quot; you should never respond, &amp;quot;no, we&amp;#39;re outside playing frisbee!&amp;quot; Instead, you should build, &amp;quot;yes, and the waitress is a robot!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in college, I had an instructor whose response to any student comment would always start with &amp;quot;no.&amp;quot; Over the course of the semester, this became a running joke with the students in the class, because it didn&amp;#39;t matter how right your answer was. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;A typical example would be the instructor asking, &amp;quot;What programming construct am I using here?&amp;quot; A student would answer, &amp;quot;you&amp;#39;re using a for loop&amp;quot; And the response would come back, &amp;quot;No. Well, I guess it is a for loop. But I wanted you to say a control statement.&amp;quot; That one&amp;#39;s actually pretty tame, because both the student&amp;#39;s response and the instructor&amp;#39;s expected response could be considered correct. But this instructor would go through verbal gymnastics to always start with no, even if the student&amp;#39;s response was precisely correct and there was no alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, many students shut down completely. Even though we joked about the instructor&amp;#39;s love of &amp;quot;no&amp;quot; many people became (consciously or unconsciously) scared off from responding. By the end of the course, I was essentially the only one brave enough to raise my hand, knowing that no matter what I said I would get a negative response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/YesAnd.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Yes And&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, most teachers don&amp;#39;t go to this extreme. But, I know how easy it is to slip into a frame of mind where you want one particular response and no one is &amp;quot;getting it.&amp;quot; So, I make a concerted effort to always start my response to students with &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot; or something else similarly positive. &amp;quot;Sure, that model has some of the qualities I&amp;#39;m describing here. That&amp;#39;s a nice connection to the stuff we were talking about last week. I was looking for one of the models we&amp;#39;ve been discussing today. Does anyone have another idea?&amp;quot; In fact, I try to start with something positive, even if the answer is partly/mostly wrong. For each incorrect response, I try to put myself into my student&amp;#39;s frame of mind and figure out what the connection is that made them say it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I go through several responses and no one is saying what I expected, I&amp;#39;ll eventually say something like, &amp;quot;oh boy, here I go again, expecting you guys to read my mind!&amp;quot; Usually, this gets a laugh from the class. And by explicitly calling myself out when I&amp;#39;m asking unreasonable questions, it helps me reduce that behavior. Sometimes students can even be frustrated by my positivism, because they want to know &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; answer to the question. Since I&amp;#39;ll talk my way through almost any response, it detracts from the idea of a correct response. While I try to strike a balance, I think that the idea of many correct responses is very statistical. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/teaching/2014/08/01/Yes-And.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/teaching/2014/08/01/Yes-And.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/YesAnd.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Code + Ed</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, I had the opportunity to attend the &lt;a href=&quot;http://eyeofestival.com/&quot;&gt;eyeo festival&lt;/a&gt; as a student volunteer. For me, one of the most useful parts of the festival was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://eyeofestival.com/code-ed-summit/&quot;&gt;Code+ed Summit&lt;/a&gt;, which took place on the day before the official conference opening. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second annual meeting of the summit (which I also attended last year) and it&amp;#39;s organized as an un-conference/wiki-style conference, meaning that there&amp;#39;s no set schedule when you arrive. Instead, the participants build the schedule as they arrive, writing down topics they want to talk about themselves or things they&amp;#39;d like to hear others discuss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s what the board looked like when we arrived:
&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/2014-06-10 08.33.25.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Blank whiteboard&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What the board looked like when we showed up. (Shoutout to the awesome &lt;a href=&quot;http://intermediaarts.org/&quot;&gt;Intermedia Arts&lt;/a&gt; space!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that there are a number of different physical spaces available at all times, with sizes that accommodate from 10 people to &amp;quot;a lot.&amp;quot; The time is broken into four sessions, two before and two after lunch. I didn&amp;#39;t get a shot of the full schedule, but here&amp;#39;s what it looked like as people started arriving and filling it up. 
&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/2014-06-10 09.23.14.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Filling it in&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;As people started filling in the board.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shot isn&amp;#39;t much better, but maybe you have an OCR algorithm that can catch all the names:
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who did the &amp;quot;designing hardware for learning and hacking&amp;quot;? That session sounds rad &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23eyeo2014&amp;amp;src=hash&quot;&gt;#eyeo2014&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/4R4JMcXBxo&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/4R4JMcXBxo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kawandeep Virdee (@whichlight) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whichlight/statuses/476480289812672512&quot;&gt;June 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tegabrain.com/&quot;&gt;Tega Brain&lt;/a&gt; started a collaborative &amp;quot;hackpad&amp;quot; (hadn&amp;#39;t heard of this site before) so people could contribute notes, and those are available &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeedeyeo.hackpad.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Uncharacteristically, I wasn&amp;#39;t taking good notes or tweeting during the summit, I think because I was so engaged in the material! With that said, here are some of my takeaways, in what I think is chronological order. If you want to know more about the summit, I really recommend the &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeedeyeo.hackpad.com/&quot;&gt;hackpad&lt;/a&gt;. There are many differing perspectives there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big data and data science for beginners&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the first session, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.blprnt.com/&quot;&gt;Jer Thorpe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flong.com/bio/en/&quot;&gt;Golan Levin&lt;/a&gt; and I led a session on teaching big data and data science to beginners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were talking about the skills that beginners really need. Do they need to understand SQL? Web scraping? Complex joins? Spinning up Amazon EC2 instances? I don&amp;#39;t know if we got all the way to this in the discussion, but I think these questions really point to a need for a second course. Do whatever you want in the first course (I don&amp;#39;t even think it needs to be the &amp;quot;easy&amp;quot; stuff, as long as it&amp;#39;s interesting) and resolve to cover the other stuff in the next one. This takes the pressure off fitting it all in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this was the session in which we were talking about responsible web scrapers. Sometimes, scraping looks like &amp;quot;hacking,&amp;quot; especially if you&amp;#39;re someone who doesn&amp;#39;t know much about hacking. To alleviate this tension, someone (probably Jer) has his students include some text with their scaper, saying something like &amp;quot;we&amp;#39;re students in Jer Thorpe&amp;#39;s data art class. If you want to know what we&amp;#39;re doing with your data, feel free to contact us at this email address.&amp;quot; This simple act can change the way people view the scraper, and afterward they got overwhelmingly positive responses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my experience, if you&amp;#39;re going to teach &amp;quot;data science&amp;quot; to beginners, you need to make sure that the vocabulary that you&amp;#39;re teaching is very limited. Obviously, this can expand as the students gain experience, but it&amp;#39;s crucial not to overwhelm them at first. I got a laugh with something like, &amp;quot;we&amp;#39;ve been very specific about the syntaxes we use with the students. Syntaxii? Syntaxonomies?&amp;quot; (Pretty sure it&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;syntaxes&amp;quot;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New medium for education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t totally know what this theme meant, but we certainly had some interesting discussions. The two I remember most distinctly were focused on the iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned the &amp;quot;navigate/drive&amp;quot; strategy that is often useful when people are learning at the computer, especially if equipment is limited. One person (the navigator) is more of the thinker, deciding what the pair should be doing. The other (the driver) actually has their hands on the keyboard/mouse. After a set period of time, participants switch roles. This can be a bit freeing, because the driver doesn&amp;#39;t need to be focusing on the strategy as much, just the technical difficulties, and the navigator doesn&amp;#39;t get caught up in syntax issues. However, it takes a certain type of person to enjoy this breakdown. Personally, I know that when I&amp;#39;m talking about computer tasks with someone (often a student) I am just itching to get my hands on the keyboard. However, it&amp;#39;s definitely a better pedagogical strategy to have them do it themselves! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same vein, one participant in the &amp;quot;new medium&amp;quot; discussion said that his significant other, who is a teacher, uses an iPad in her elementary school classroom. At any given time, one student is chosen as &amp;quot;The Finger,&amp;quot; which means that they are the one who gets to touch the iPad. This is a fun role for the person who gets to be The Finger, and it really focuses the attention of the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another participant had worked with one of the Federal executive departments, and was on a team that had something to do with daily briefings of top officials*. Typically, these briefs are created as pdfs and distributed as printed documents. But, a much more engaging way to display the information is to have an iPad app so that the official can ask questions and be shown answers on-the-fly. This department changed their briefing to iPads, with the option to still receive paper briefings if the officials preferred that. One particular official* is very tech savvy and loves the iPad, but was not being briefed on the iPad. When they investigated, the department learned that it wasn&amp;#39;t the official&amp;#39;s preference, but rather the briefer&amp;#39;s. With a paper report, both official and briefer can have a copy of the brief, and the briefer can keep a respectful distance from the official.  The iPad requires a much more intimate connection, both heads bent over the iPad, manipulating the screen. It came out that the briefer felt this was disrespectful to the official. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was an interesting intersection of culture and technology. From friends who work with the US Army, I understand that it&amp;#39;s engrained in army culture for a presenter to provide paper copies of presentation slides (e.g. PowerPoint) and pay attention to the most senior official in the room. When they turn the page on their document, everyone else turns the page, and the presenter is expected to move on to the next slide. The iPad example similarly comes from a desire for the official to retain their power, rather than giving the briefer the same (or more) agency. However, it&amp;#39;s not just culture-- the iPad (or the app) could have been programmed to allow two devices to sync, so that the briefer could maintain a respectful distance but still &amp;quot;drive&amp;quot; the briefing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* I know the names of the department and the official, just trying to maintain some modicum of anonymity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language and teaching&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest takeaway I got from this session was the importance of concreteness, both in terms of language and in terms of making tangible representations. The woman who made this point was from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ideo.com/&quot;&gt;IDEO&lt;/a&gt;, and was talking more specifically about design meetings. She said that in her experience, you can talk about &amp;quot;a pen&amp;quot; but it&amp;#39;s always better to talk about &amp;quot;this pen.&amp;quot; This reminds me of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meganerinmiller.com/&quot;&gt;Megan Erin Miller&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tactiledesignkit.com/&quot;&gt;tactile design kit&lt;/a&gt;. This is a free (!) printable download that allows you to do web design using physical pieces. I saw Megan speak about this at eyeo 2013, and I was impressed with all the creativity-enhancing limits it places. For example, you can clearly see when things won&amp;#39;t all fit on a particular page, or when your buttons will overflow without some sort of collapsing menu. It would be fun to make something similar for statistics education, or even just use this same concept when planning computational projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also spent some time talking about the difference between a prototype and a provocation. I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; the difference is that a prototype is a proof of concept of something you could actually make. A provocation is something more conceptual, that you wouldn&amp;#39;t actually put into production. But, having it (again, physically) in front of a group can stimulate good conversation that wouldn&amp;#39;t happen otherwise. When you create provocations, you can make many very different iterations, instead of the many similar iterations that you might create as prototypes. Again, this is something I&amp;#39;m trying to bring into my own work. Instead of trying to conceptualize prototypes, I want to think more in terms of provocations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching coding in high school&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about &amp;quot;what doesn&amp;#39;t work&amp;quot; for quite a while in this session. I think this was a cathartic thing to do (there&amp;#39;s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; that doesn&amp;#39;t work) but it probably would have been more useful to talk about what did work. Luckily, we did transition there eventually. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was glad to hear that most schools are moving away from things like Java and C++ towards simpler scripting languages, at least outside of AP Computer Science. Several people in the session were teaching Processing (even in high school geometry), and I also heard mention of JavaScript. I mostly teach high school &lt;em&gt;teachers&lt;/em&gt;, and (of course) I&amp;#39;m teaching them R within RStudio. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all seemed to agree that for effective computer science teaching, you need to find a balance between open-endedness and unpreparedness. It&amp;#39;s important to know that the problem can be solved, or that there&amp;#39;s something interesting there, but you don&amp;#39;t want to have come up with &amp;quot;the answer,&amp;quot; otherwise it won&amp;#39;t feel creative and interesting to students. We all also agreed that finding these interesting prompts is pretty tricky. One successful coding exercise that a teacher set was creating a &amp;quot;choose your own adventure&amp;quot; narrative using HTML pages. Students could make the narrative as complicated or as simple as they wanted, so it scaled well, and they could customize to their interests. The teacher who told this anecdote admitted that his example story was pretty simple and uninteresting, but that his students really ran with it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was talking about the &amp;quot;recipe&amp;quot; idea that I&amp;#39;ve seen come up in some research on teaching/learning Java. Greenfoot (a learning environment for Java) uses the philosophy that students should never start with a blank page. Instead, they should be able to modify one line and then run something and have a result. This is like a recipe. &amp;quot;Starting from a blank screen requires design, and is an advanced exercise. It is something students encounter later, but not as the first contact&amp;quot; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://kar.kent.ac.uk/30614/1/2010-11-TOCE-greenfoot.pdf&quot;&gt;Michael K&amp;ouml;lling&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another universal is that humans tend to view any change as bad change. So, if you&amp;#39;re going to show a few different tools you really need to scaffold the transition. It needs to seem like, &amp;quot;oh, we&amp;#39;ve reached the edge of the capabilities of this tool. I really wish we could do [X]&amp;quot; and then give them the tool to do [X]. But, you need to build up. If the new tool can&amp;#39;t do the things that the old tool could, it&amp;#39;s going to feel like a downgrade. A teacher gave the example of starting with Processing and then trying to sell students on R. As you might expect, that transition didn&amp;#39;t feel good to the students. Similarly, I&amp;#39;ve found that people will complain about any tool you give them, but if you try to change it they will complain! Similarly, any time the interface to a social networking site changes, all you see are complaints. Humans hate change!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The pitch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, the Code+ed summit gave me tons of inspiration for my teaching practice and dissertation. I love the eyeo festival, but I think I get more actionable ideas from the summit. If I haven&amp;#39;t already made the pitch to you, allow me to do it now: the summit has been free to attend so far, and you can register separately from the eyeo festival. The eyeo festival sells out within minutes every year, but the Code+ed summit fills at a more civilized rate. And, there are often a few people who don&amp;#39;t show up, so you can also test your luck by just showing up at Intermedia Arts on the day of the summit and asking if they have space. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the best part is because it&amp;#39;s an unconference, you can make sure that it fits your interests. People have asked me, &amp;quot;was there a session on [X]?&amp;quot; and even if the answer is no, there could be next year! It&amp;#39;s a very casual event, and great for networking. If you work anywhere in the space of education and computation, I recommend attending!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P.S., it was only as I was writing this post that I noticed that the name &amp;quot;Code+ed&amp;quot; can be read as &amp;quot;Code and Education&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;coded&amp;quot; (which itself has two meanings; either programmed or as in &amp;quot;coded language&amp;quot;). Nice job with the naming, organizers!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2014/07/22/Coded.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/conferences/2014/07/22/Coded.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/2014-06-10 09.23.14.jpg" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sweater variation; or grey != black and white</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I have a sweater that I&amp;#39;ve loved to death (if you&amp;#39;ve encountered me anytime in the last 5 years, you&amp;#39;ve probably seen it) and after many frustrating attempts to replace it with something similar, I took to eBay to try to find an exact replacement. This is something I&amp;#39;ve had success with in the past-- put in some information about the item, and make a saved search that emails me every day with newly-listed results. But I&amp;#39;ve learned that eBay sellers only know about the mean, and not about variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eBay saved search goes something like this-- &amp;quot;H&amp;amp;M cardigan Color:Gray&amp;quot; but I&amp;#39;ve found that I often get results like this:
&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/BlackAndWhiteCardigan.JPG&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Black and white sweater&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is one of classification-- eBay provides the standard six colors (primary and secondary), and a few descriptors like beige, ivory and brown, but probably the best description of the sweater above is &amp;quot;Multi-Color&amp;quot; which doesn&amp;#39;t really capture it. Probably eBay should provide a &amp;quot;Black and White&amp;quot; option. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I think is funny about this example is that the seller is partially right-- the typical color of this sweater &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; gray. But I&amp;#39;m not interested just in the typical color. I&amp;#39;m looking for a sweater with limited color variation (consistency across the garment). I&amp;#39;m looking for a unimodal color distribution with a small standard deviation, not a bimodal one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is abusing terminology a bit, but I think it illustrates an important point about how we don&amp;#39;t always care about the typical value, and when we talk about distributions (in any sense) we also need to take into account the variability. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/misc/2014/06/12/Sweater_Variation.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/misc/2014/06/12/Sweater_Variation.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/BlackAndWhiteCardigan.JPG" />
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>That paper I was telling you to read</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I was joking at lunch with some colleagues that I should have a few of my favorite papers linked on the main page of my website, so when I reference them for the n^th time, I can just say &amp;quot;look at my website&amp;quot; instead of promising to email them. While I don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s reasonable to put this on my front page, here&amp;#39;s the current list of my &amp;quot;have you read [x]?&amp;quot; papers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://r.cs.purdue.edu/pub/ecoop12.pdf&quot;&gt;Evaluating the Design of the R Language&lt;/a&gt;: I&amp;#39;ll admit, I don&amp;#39;t understand everything that&amp;#39;s in this paper. And it certainly wasn&amp;#39;t necessary to sell me on R! But, I interact with a lot of computer scientists who ask me &amp;quot;why R?&amp;quot; and this paper seems to be a much better answer than anything I manage to come up with. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;ftp://cm.bell-labs.com/cm/stat/tukey/memo/techtools.html&quot;&gt;Technical Tools of Statistics&lt;/a&gt;: Tukey&amp;#39;s vision of the future, from the 1960s. Interesting because we&amp;#39;re &lt;strong&gt;still&lt;/strong&gt; trying to figure this stuff out. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://softwarestudies.com/cultural_analytics/Six_Provocations_for_Big_Data.pdf&quot;&gt;Six Provocations for Big Data&lt;/a&gt;: This article, by danah boyd and Kate Crawford, gives a great response to the buzzword trend of &amp;quot;Big Data.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vis.stanford.edu/files/2011-DataWrangling-IVJ.pdf&quot;&gt;Research Directions in Data Wrangling&lt;/a&gt;: Just a great paper summing up some directions for research/development in the realm of data processes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jonathanstray.com/papers/wickham.pdf&quot;&gt;Graphical Inference for InfoVis&lt;/a&gt;: Using an array of plots, most of them with &amp;quot;null&amp;quot; data, to determine if patterns you&amp;#39;re seeing are real or just the result of randomness. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;thumb&quot; href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/overviewperm.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; alt=&quot;Permuted basketball&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Permuted graphic showing the location of Lakers players when they made 3-point shots. Which do you think is the real data?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/papers/2014/05/16/That_Paper.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/blog/papers/2014/05/16/That_Paper.html</guid>
				<media:thumbnail url="http://www.science.smith.edu/~amcnamara/img/overviewperm.jpg" />
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>